<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian and wholesom admonition directed to the Frenchmen, which are reuolted from true religion, and haue polluted themselues with the superstition and idolatrie of poperie.</title>
            <title>Remonstrance chrestienne et salutaire. English</title>
            <author>Constant, Léonard, d. 1610.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1587</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18639</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5154</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120782</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855976</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855976</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21489</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18639)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21489)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1198:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian and wholesom admonition directed to the Frenchmen, which are reuolted from true religion, and haue polluted themselues with the superstition and idolatrie of poperie.</title>
                  <title>Remonstrance chrestienne et salutaire. English</title>
                  <author>Constant, Léonard, d. 1610.</author>
                  <author>Fetherston, Christopher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[144] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, dwelling in Distaffe Lane, neere the signe of the Castle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1587]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Christopher Fetherstone, of: Constant, Léonard.  "Remonstrance chrestienne et salutaire", Geneva, 1586. The author's name is ambiguously mentioned by an exhortatory poem on A6r, line 2 from bottom, referring to the path 'Which constant hath proposde to you.'--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An admonition to the Frenchmen.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A¹⁰ B-H I⁶.</note>
                  <note>A1, title page, backed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21489:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21489:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>1587. A CHRISTIAN and wholeſom <hi>Admonition,</hi> Directed to the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>which are reuolted</hi> from true religion, and haue polluted themſelues with the ſuperſtition and Idolatrie of Poperie.</p>
            <p>LONDON <hi>Printed by Iohn Wolfe,</hi> dwelling in Diſtaffe Lane, neare the ſigne of the Caſtle.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="song">
            <pb facs="tcp:21489:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21489:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A ſong or ſonnet of the authour</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a graue conteſtation and complaint of the Lord, againſt the vnthankfulnes, cowardlines, and diſloyaltie of the French reuolts, a denunciation of their extreame woe, if they continue reuolts ſtill and an exhortation to turne to him.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>HEare heauen and earth, and all things els,</l>
               <l>Which th'ample cope of heauen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains:</l>
               <l>Heare my iuſt plaints touching the fall,</l>
               <l>Of people which in Fraunce remaines.</l>
               <l>Whoſe faint and feeble faith did fail</l>
               <l>When th'enimie did it aſſaile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What moued thee my couenant</l>
               <l>Vnthankfullie thus to forſake:</l>
               <l>That thou thy ſelfe mightſt ioine to Baal</l>
               <l>His curſed waies that thou mightſt take?</l>
               <l>O people moſt vnthankfull then,</l>
               <l>O moſt ingratefull ſonnes of men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell me if that at anie time,</l>
               <l>I dealt with thee vncourteouſly?</l>
               <l>What meanes this change? hopſt thou to find</l>
               <l>Thy good or thy felicitie?</l>
               <l>If thou eſtranged be from me,</l>
               <l>In whom all good things are that be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O curſed wretch? O madding foole?</l>
               <l>Thou haſt (that thou thy ſelfe mightſt ſaue)</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21489:3"/>
               <l>Thy ſelfe bewrapt in Satans nets,</l>
               <l>Who both thy bodie and ſoule will haue,</l>
               <l>And ſure he will thy goods deſtroy,</l>
               <l>To thy great griefe and ſore annoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bethinke thy ſelfe. Condemne thy fault,</l>
               <l>Returne to me whoſe merci's great.</l>
               <l>A pardon is prepared for thoſe,</l>
               <l>Which thorow faith ſhall it intreat.</l>
               <l>Which teares from dewe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eyes let fall,</l>
               <l>And vnto me for mercie call.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21489:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Chriſtian Reader.</hi> O Lord ſtrengthen vs, that wee may fight thy battell, ſtand by vs, or els we can not preuaile. Giue vs faith, and we ſhall haue victorie for euer. Amen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Anie men are of many minds. And few there are, that accept thankefully the labours of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, in theſe vnthankefull and laſt times. Yea it may be, they will thinke the publiſhing of this booke to be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, conſidering that we, neither (thankes be to God) now ſuffer, or are like to ſuffer perſecution. For amongſt vs, Gods word is preached, the Churches are in peace; and flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: all things goe with with vs, and not againſt vs. Againe, the goſpel hauing continued ſo long, by all likelihood, it taketh ſuch deepe root, as we ſhall not need to feare, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in, or ſpringing vp againe of Poperie. In deed, if theſe things were as they ought to be, receiued, followed, and obeyed: if men did know, and would confeſſe the goodnes of
<pb facs="tcp:21489:4"/> the Lord in calling them, and vouchſafing them ſo manie mercies, in waiting ſo long for worthie fruites of their conuerſion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: then no doubt, we ſhould the leſſe neede to feare that which our ſins doe threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: that in ſo great light, and after ſo manie happie dayes: in the broad day of ſo manie graces of knowledge &amp; wiſedom of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vnto men, that euer either darke po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie in the courſe of Idolatrie or hereſie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme, or ſuch like iniquitie ſhould euer ſo grow again, as that perſecution ſhould be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. But none of theſe things giue vs anie comfort. For howſoeuer Gods word be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, (which yet is done with great corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that as ſcantlie as may be) yet it is not followed. We haue in deed ſome outward peace, but the ſpirituall peace of God, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie eſtabliſhed in the Miniſterie of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, that is farre from vs: for alacke, we are waxed wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at home, &amp; we preſcribe God abroad according to our owne luſts, in the matters of his owne worſhip: we eate and drinke with the drunkard, and ſay: Our maiſter is gone into a farre iourney, and will be long a comming home. Gods enimies, the <hi>Amorites</hi> and <hi>Edomites</hi> may doe what they will, and the way is not taken that
<pb facs="tcp:21489:4"/> ſhould ſtocke vp by the roote theſe curſed fruites and wicked generations. For they haue long looked, though God in fauour and long patience haue waited for our repentance and therefore diſappointed them, for the day, wherein they might once againe leade vs forth as ſheepe to the cruel ſlaughter. And what ſhall we ſay. Is not God iuſt, that hee ſhould chaſtice his children and be obeyed of his enimies? Yes verelie. In all times the godlie haue, and muſt beare their croſſes. As long as Chriſt ſhall haue a Church on earth, Antichriſt ſhall haue his Sinagogue. There will euer be children of the fleſh, to perſecute thoſe that are of the ſpirit. And therefore thoſe that dreame of an earthly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, they deceyue them ſelues: for it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that Gods ſeruants ſhould haue their heauen in this world. God hath his cup in his hand fully mixed. His children muſt not onely kiſſe the cuppe, and drinke the firſt draught, but alſo his enimies ſhall ſweepe vp the dregges euen to the bottom. Wherefore my good brother, whoſoeuer thou art, reade ſuch like exhortations as this is. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer God ſhall worke, pray that thou maieſt abide ſuch fierie tryals as he doth ſee meete and expedient for thee. Looke not vpon men,
<pb facs="tcp:21489:5"/> but looke vpon the truth of thy God. All the men of the world, ſhall not be able to ſtand to plead any thy leaſt reuolt from the truth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the almighty God. Therefore neither for liuing nor land, for life nor limme, deny not the leaſt iot of his euerlaſting will. In time of peace, while it is yet ſommer, prouide againſt winter. Before the ſtormes come, prepare the cables. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the anker that may hold the ſhip faſt in all dangers. For ſurely God will come, he can not but viſite, that he may purge this land fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hipocriſes, will-worſhips, vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties &amp; follies, wherewith it is in a manner o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelmed euerie where. And albeit this be to be looked for, yet feare not thou, whoſoeuer thou be that art Gods childe. <hi>For theſe rods ſhall be for thy good. Thine eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies crueltie ſhall bring thee to feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, and themſelues to euerlaſting woe. God will make way for thee, to eſcape all peril. Though they would ſend thee to hell, yet thou ſhalt goe to heauen. In killing thee, they ſhall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor thee, and thou ſhalt liue for euer.</hi> The grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt be with thee. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21489:5"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>worſhipfull, godly, vertuous, and</hi> my ſingular good friends, M. Henry Neuill Eſquier, and Maiſtreſſe Anne Neuill his wife, grace and peace with increaſe of godlie zeale.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worſhipfull, ſithence my firſt acquaintance had with you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch hath been the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall courſe of your manyfolde courteſies towards me, as that if I ſhould not ſeeke in ſome, though not in ſemblable ſort to requite them, I might iuſtlie be counted a man moſt vnthankfull, if vnthankfull perſons deſerue the names of men. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe mine abilitie is in no caſe ſuch, as that I can in ſuch ſort, as willingly
<pb facs="tcp:21489:6"/> I woulde make equall recompence for the ſame: I muſt content my ſelfe in ſuch ſort as I can to doe it. And therefore as one repaying ſhales for nuts, or ſhreds for whole cloth, I thought meete to preſent vnto your hands theſe my ſimple labours, being the firſt fruites of my ſlender knowledge in the French tongue, as a token and teſtimonie of my thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and duetie, which for good cauſes I owe vnto you both, but prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallie in regard of that zeale of Gods glory wherewith it hath pleaſed him to inflame both your harts, and that in ſuch ſort as that you ſeeme to bee good meanes appointed of God to prouoke others. As touching the worke it ſelfe (right worſhipfull) and the neceſsitie thereof, I neede not ſpeake, ſeeing it hath pleaſed God that ſomewhat ſhould be ſaid as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by my verie louing brother M.
<pb facs="tcp:21489:6"/> I. F. touching the neceſsitie &amp; times of the argument euen for theſe times whereto I referre you. And thus beſeeching you moſt humblie to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this ſimple mite at mine hands, and to pardon my boldnes in preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to make you patronize ſo ſimple a worke, regarding mine own labours, I commit you to the tuition of the Almightie, beſeeching him to worke farther in you a true zeale of his glorie, that you may zealouſly pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceed in that courſe of godlines which you haue begunne.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your worſhips much bounden and at commandement in the Lord.</hi> Chriſtopher Fetherſtone.</signed> 
               <dateline>At Maighfield in Suſſex <date>this 24, of Iune. 1587.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:21489:7"/>
            <head>A Sonnet made by way of <hi>exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to the Frenchmen which are</hi> reuolted from true religion, to the end they may returne to God.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>O Frenchmen which were once belou'd,</l>
               <l>With loue ſurpaſſing that of men:</l>
               <l>Of God, who had by ſundrie ſignes,</l>
               <l>The ſame reueald to you as then.</l>
               <l>But now that God you haue forſaken,</l>
               <l>And part with Romiſh idoll taken.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What ſpirite? what counſaile? or what rage,</l>
               <l>So carrieth you? what hope? what feare:</l>
               <l>Doth make you turne: yea ſo reuolt</l>
               <l>From him that loued you ſo deare?</l>
               <l>O blockiſhnes which Sathan breedes,</l>
               <l>Not once to ſee whither he you leader,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What? will you then forſake for earth,</l>
               <l>The holie heauens? what? hazard all</l>
               <l>To gaine a thing that's nothing worth?</l>
               <l>What thing more precious can you call,</l>
               <l>Then God, the ſoule, and bodie neate,</l>
               <l>And honour, which are riches great?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You looſe all thoſe if you proceed,</l>
               <l>In courſe which you haue erſt begunne:</l>
               <l>Returne to God. Vp, courage take,</l>
               <l>And to that path full ſwiftlie runne,</l>
               <l>Which conſtant hath propoſde to you,</l>
               <l>Vp, vp, I ſay and enter now.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21489:7"/>
            <head>A CHRISTIAN AND <hi>wholeſom admonition, directed to</hi> the French-men which are reuolted from true religion, and haue polluted themſelues with the ſuperſtitions and Idolatries of Poperie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt the effects of true godlineſſe, this ought by good right to be placed in the firſt place, as being chiefe, or to ſpeake plainely, the onely duetie of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, foraſmuch as vnder it, it compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth all the reſt: that is in ſumme, that we be in ſuch ſort inforced with the zeale of Gods houſe, that when we ſhall ſee his holie and ſacred name diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and blaſphemed by worldlie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane men, and our poore neighbors for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the enſigne of their ſoueraigne Lord &amp; maiſter, forſaking their fellowes, and taking part with the enimie of their ſaluation, we be thereby more moued and touched to the quicke, then by anie thing that can befall vs. By this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing or touching I meane chiefly two
<pb facs="tcp:21489:8"/> things: the firſt is, that being diſpleaſed and grieued when we ſee ſuch offences as redound to the diſhonor of God, and to the deſtruction and vtter ruine of our poore neighbors, we humble our ſelues in the preſence of our God, renting, not our garments, but our hurt, with wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, faſting, mourning, and feruent prayers to the Lord, that it may pleaſe him to ſet vp on foot againe thoſe of his elect which are fallen through infirmity, and to ſtrengthen thoſe other whom hee hath preſerued by his goodnes, giuing them grace to perſiſt conſtantlie euen vntill the end, in the profeſſion of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie name. The ſecond is, that euerie man according to his vocation doe faithfullie employ the gifts and graces which hee hath receyued at the hands of God, to the maintenance of his glorie, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and further ſo much as in him lieth, the ſaluation of his neighbors.</p>
            <p>And ſurely ſo it is, that the moſt faithfull ſeruants of God haue alwaies done this: yea euen at this day alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie good men doe it, whom the Lord hath preſerued through his grace from the rage of this laſt tempeſt: which doe not
<pb facs="tcp:21489:8"/> onely wéepe &amp; mourne, being extreamly grieued and vexed, to ſee the ruines and deſolations of the poore Churches in Fraunce, and to ſee the precious name of the Lord blaſphemed and diſhonoured by the moſt ſtraunge kind of reuolting that euer was ſeene in the Church: but ouer and beſides this, they ſtrengthen them ſelues euerie man according to his abilitie to repaire the breaches, and to doe what in them lyeth, that this euill may goe no further. Now as for me, I haue obtained this honour through the mercie of God, that I ſhould be of the number of thoſe which being dedicated and conſecrated to his ſeruice, haue not onely their harts wounded and pearced through with the beholding of ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders and confuſions, which are as it were a deluge or inundation of euils, wherewith the whole earth in a maner is couered: but alſo deſire for their part to procure ſome wholeſome remedies for theſe maladies.</p>
            <p>And therefore I determined to write ſome briefe admonition, which I meant to direct to thoſe whom God had particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larlie committed to me: and not to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb facs="tcp:21489:9"/> the ſame, directing it to all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in generall. Which was not for want of good will toward my brethren in the Lord, and toward all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Ieſus Chriſt: but knowing mine owne infirmitie and inſufficiencie, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer durſt haue interpriſed it without the prouocation or rather iniunction of my brethren and companions in the Lords worke, which haue charged mee with this, what reaſons ſoeuer I could allege for mine excuſe. Which thing I meant to ſet downe by way of preface, that the cauſes which induced mee to write this admonition might be made known. The which I addreſſe vnto all thoſe in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, who hauing ſometimes made open profeſſion of religion, haue now forſaken the ſame: alwaies prouided that there remaine in them as yet ſome remnant of true godlines, of good conſcience, and of the feare of God, and ſome hope of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion. And this belongeth principally to you Frenchmen, who heretofore haue taken part with true and pure religion, making proteſtation before God and his Angels, that you would liue and dye in it, and haue ſo forſaken the impieties,
<pb facs="tcp:21489:9"/> ſuperſtition and idolatries of poperie, that you did ſolemnly promiſe neuer to returne to the ſame againe, yea though you ſhould looſe not onely your goods, honours, and other temporall commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but alſo your liues. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the onely feare leaſt you ſhould looſe theſe things, and the vaine imagination leaſt you ſhould ſuffer ſome diſcmomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie by following Ieſus Chriſt, made you breake your vow and promiſe to God, and hath drawne you aſide verie quickly out of the right way of his truth, yea euen to the great diſhonour of his maieſtie, to the offence of his Church, and to your owne vtter deſtruction, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you repent. To you it is, I ſay, that I direct this my worke particularlie, that I may louingly and brotherlie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre with you, touching the offence which you haue committed: beſeeching you in the name of the liuing God, that you would find ſome ſpare time to reade it, pondering together with me the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which ſhall be therein ſet downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your eyes, out of the word of God. And that not onelie to the end you may approue the ſame (as all thoſe will not ſticke to doe, which will not flatter them
<pb facs="tcp:21489:10"/> ſelues, nor ſtubbornlie withſtand the trueth of God) but aboue all that hauing approued the ſame, there may be in you an holie reſolution, accompanied with the effect thereof: that is in ſumme, that you may with ſpeede repaire by a true and readie conuerſion that fault which you haue committed. Which being well conſidered and weighed, as it ought, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the circumſtances thereof, you ſhall full well know, and ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to graunt, that it is nothing ſo ſmall and light as the enimies of your ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would make you belieue, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the diuel, the fleſh, and the worlde, which indeuour moreouer to caſt you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a déepe ſléepe, and ſo to beſot you, that you may not anie longer haue anie fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of your faults, but may more and more plunge your ſelues in filth &amp; mire, that you may there continue, and finally become Antechriſts, a people without God and without religion, that is to ſay, being wholie become ſlaues to Sathan, as is befallen to more people in our coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie of Fraunce, then were to be wiſhed, through the iuſt iudgement of God. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, when you ſhall well perceiue
<pb facs="tcp:21489:10"/> the greatnes and hugenes of your fall, it muſt needes come to paſſe that you ſhall ſee the horrible &amp; fearefull iudgements and vengeance, which the Lord bringeth vpon all thoſe, who through their ſlack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe an diſloyaltie, haue beene the cauſe that his holie name hath béene profaned, and their neighbors offended. Which knowledge may ſerue to bring you to a true deiection and humilitie before the maieſtie of God: not that you may faint and ſinke down vnder your burden, and ſo fall into deſpaire, through the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of your tranſgreſſions, and by the ſight of Gods iuſtice: but rather that being by this meanes humbled in the preſence of God, you may be the better brought to draw neare vnto him: or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſpeake more properly, to prouoke him to draw nearer to you: according to that which the Prophet ſaith, that <hi>The Lord is nigh vnto thoſe that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortles, beaten downe, and broken in hart,</hi> and ſaueth them that be of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite ſpirite, euen through the feeling of their ſinnes and iniquities: ſo that a man may truelie ſay, that ſuch humilitie is as it were the firſt gate or dore to enter in
<pb facs="tcp:21489:11"/> vnto the throne of the grace and mercie of God: who is in ſuch ſort iuſt to puniſh ſinners in his wrath, euen thoſe which are obſtinate, and which harden their harts when they heare his voice, and abuſe his patience, that he is alſo readie to ſhow mercie, he is pitifull, gentle, and merciful to all thoſe which being conuict in their conſcience, and hauing accuſed themſelues before God, returne vnto him without faining, throwing them ſelues as it were into the armes of his moſt bountifull father, to ſecke for grace at his hands.</p>
            <p>Theſe are (my brethren) the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall points which I mean, by the grace of God, to laie open vnto you in this my preſent writing: that is, a briefe collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that which you muſt doe, that you may eſcape the iuſt wrath and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord, and bee reconciled to him. This is that which I require at your hands, for the glorie of God, and for your owne benefit and ſaluation: this is that which all your brethren &amp; mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers (whom God hath preſerued) deſire and craue daylie at the hands of God with gronings, ſighes, and moſt feruent
<pb facs="tcp:21489:11"/> praiers. This is that which the Angels of heauen looke for at your handes, that they may reioyce and praiſe God for your conuerſion: Briefly, this is that whereunto you are called and inuited by the goodneſſe and clemencie of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie father, who ſtretcheth out his armes vnto you, to imbrace you as his children. Wherfore it ſtandeth you vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon to looke to it: for the caſe ſo ſtandeth that you muſt now either honour or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour God, you muſt either be ſaued, or elſe condemned?</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as my deſire is to help &amp; comfort you therein, I wil take paine, through Gods help, to make theſe things more plaine, &amp; ſomewhat more largely &amp; in order to deduct them. Firſt of al then, if you be deſirous to come to the true knowledge of your fault that you may deteſt the ſame, &amp; obtaine pardon for it at the handes of God, you muſt beware that you weigh it not in a falſe ballance, ſuch as is that of Satans, the fleſh, &amp; the world, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſworne enimies of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for theſe ſhal not be your iudges at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt day: but you muſt peyze the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſeales of the wil of God, which is declared vnto
<pb facs="tcp:21489:12"/> vs in his word: for that is the onlie moſt certaine, and moſt perfect rule whereto all our actions muſt be referred, &amp; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they muſt al be hedged in, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the which alone men ſhal bée iudged of the Lord.</p>
            <p>I know full well that all thoſe which haue forgotten themſelues in this caſe, forſaking the profeſſion of true religion, that they may raunge themſelues vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> banner Antichriſt, muſt not be placed in one &amp; the ſame ranke. For one ſort is ſo fallen that they are as it were out of all hope euer to be able to riſe againe, of which ſort are that heape and rabble of hypocrites, which had intruded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into the Church of God, making a ſhow y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they would folow Ieſus Chriſt, and make profeſſion of his Goſpell: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, foraſmuch as they neuer had anie ſparkle of true godlines, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anie will to renounce their concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcences, and the vanities of this world, that they might dedicate &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to God, to follow Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; to reforme their life according to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of his Goſpel, it is come to paſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their hypocriſie is diſcouered: for ſéeing
<pb facs="tcp:21489:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> they could not (ſo long as they profeſſed religion) giue their luſtes the bridle, and run into al filthineſſe, diſſolutenes, and infamous facts: giue ouer themſelues to their delights and filthy pleaſure, ſatiſfie their ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; couetouſnes, enioy their eaſe, delicates, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities of this life, take their paſtime, and ſo liue in ſuch reſt according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might not bée diſquieted or troubled any maner of way Briefly, ſeing they coulde not ſerue two maiſters which were quite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, God &amp; the Diuell, they forſook God &amp; gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, which is as it were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuels bawd: other ſome ſtaid not til they might be tried by the fan of perſecutions, &amp; ſo to go out of the church, but they reuolted of their own accord at ſundry times, &amp; vpon diuers occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, either becauſe they could not abide to be reproued for their faults &amp; offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, or els bicauſe they wold not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their neck to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yoke of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; range the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues according to the order of the church as others did, or els bicauſe they could not addict the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world as hath bin ſaid. This was the cauſe why they ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt
<pb facs="tcp:21489:13"/> ſtumbling ſtone whereon they light in the way, nay rather they went purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſéeke the ſame. Otherſome haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the croſſe &amp; perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And albeit the moſt part of theſe men make a ſhew y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they approue our religion, &amp; yet to the end they may be counted good Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, are more ſuperſtitious, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to ceremonies then others, yet ſo it is that they be very Epicures &amp; Atheiſts, which in their harts deride al religion. As for this ſort of men, we may rather deſire it than euer hope for it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wil euer be brought to a true knowledge of their offence, that they may turne vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord: For the Prince of darkneſſe hath ſtricken the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſuch blindnes, through the iuſt iudgement of God, that they are in greater darknes of beaſtly ignorance, as touching the knowledge of their fault, then they were before they came to the knowledge of the trueth. And it fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with them as with him that in a dark night co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to put out a candle or light wherewith he was inlightened a while, for afterward his eies dazel more, &amp; he is in worſe caſe than before hee had that light. Therfore no maruaile if theſe
<pb facs="tcp:21489:13"/> men be ſo turned out of the right way, that they cannot returne into the ſame againe. For as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>If thoſe which haue once bin illuminated, and haue taſted of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly gift, &amp; haue bin made partakers of the holy ghoſt, and haue taſted of the good worde of God, and of the powers of the world to come:</hi> If theſe I ſaie, fall away, it is impoſſible that they ſhould be renued to repentance: ſeing they crucifie the ſon of God afreſh, ſo much as in them lieth, and make a mocke of him. Now then foraſmuch as theſe men are hardened in their wickedneſſe, &amp; ſo conſequently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable, it were but loſt labour to write to them, &amp; to exhort the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to acknowledge and ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their fault, wherfore my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is not to apply my ſelfe to them in this my writing, ſaue only to denounce againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſentence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt, ſpeaking by the Apoſtle to the Hebrues, that is, that ſéeing they haue ſinned wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly after they knew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth, that is to ſay, ſéeing that being altogether eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and cut off from the Church of Ieſus Chriſt, they take pleaſure in iniquitie, &amp; contrary to the teſtimony of their owne
<pb facs="tcp:21489:14"/> conſcience doe malitiouſlie reſiſt the knowen truth, there remaineth no more ſacrifice for ſinne for them, but a fearfull looking for iudgement, and a conſuming fire which ſhal deuour the aduerſaries. And this is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which we both can &amp; will ſaie, touching theſe men at this time.</p>
            <p>But as for you my brethren to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I now ſpeak, God wil not haue me to rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ko<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt thoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for if it were ſo, then would not I take ſo much pains as to write to you. But as I know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the more part of you there was more frailty tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> malice &amp; hatred againſt the trueth, ſo likewiſe I haue a good hope, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after the lord through his goodnes hath beheld you with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame eie wherwith he beheld S. <hi>Peter,</hi> he will make you come out of the houſe of that wicked Prieſt <hi>Caiphas,</hi> where Antichriſt &amp; his miniſters purſue Ieſus Chriſt to death, &amp; ſpit in his face with mockes, railinges and blaſphemies moſt horrible: I hope alſo that after you haue wept bitterlie for your fault, you ſhal be reconciled to God, and receiued to mercie. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding it is verie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you be awaked vp &amp; thorowly touched, leaſt you lye ſléeping in your
<pb facs="tcp:21489:14"/> ſinne, and ſo flatter your ſelues, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by excuſing or leſſening your fault, or by féeding your ſelues with I cannot tel what vaine hope, and ſo fall finallie into the ſame hardneſſe and obſtinacie whereinto manie are fallen: who when they firſt began to fal awaie, made none account alwaies to continue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> filthie ſinke: but did hope, yea &amp; perſuade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to come out thence in time: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding they haue ſuffred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be lulled faſt aſléep by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bed of their tender &amp; delicate fleſh, they driue off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> daie to daie, waiting for ſome gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den world wherein the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt might be preached without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, and the profeſſion of religion ſhould no longer bring with it the croſſe &amp; afflictions. But what? They ſée that in ſtéede of hauing an ende, theſe affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions continue, naie are redoubled con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to their hope: foraſmuch as they neuer as yet learned this leſſon which Ieſus Chriſt teacheth all thoſe which wil followe him, that is,<note place="margin">Mat. 16</note> that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and take vp their croſſe, that they maye beare it during their whole life, and that being thus prepared
<pb facs="tcp:21489:15"/> they follow him. Foraſmuch the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as theſe men ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues deceiued by their vain hope, and that they neuer tooke any time to bethinke themſelues and to ponder their fault, and to marke and conſider the iudgements of God vpon thoſe that are ſo ſlacke and diſloiall as to flie from their enſigne, at ſuche time as they are to enter the battaile: they are reſolued to forſake all, and to lie tumbling in their filth, that they may periſh miſerably, yea eternally, rather than they will ſuffer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen a little with Ieſus Chriſt, that they may raigne and be glorified with him eternally. And now my brethren to the ende you may make your profite of their follie, and that by other mens harmes you may learne to be wiſe, you muſt beware that you take not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame way which they haue taken: but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe enter you rather into your ſelues, and examine your conſcience through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without flatterie, giuing the ſame iudgement of your fault, and pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the ſame ſentence of conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your own ſelues, which you ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times gaue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe which had vſed the like ſlacknes &amp; diſloialty, to the end that
<pb facs="tcp:21489:15"/> iudging your ſelues you may not bée iudged of the Lord, as ſaith the Apoſtle. And that you may the better do this, you muſt rather hearken to the voice of God, and to the witneſſe of your owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which accuſeth you, then to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunting voice of that olde Serpent, who to the ende he may ſeduce you (as he hath alreadie made too great a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) ceaſeth not to whiſper into the eare of your conſcience, that which he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſaid to our firſt parents: <hi>and hath God ſaid, you ſhall not eate of euerie tree of the Garden, &amp;c.</hi> And if he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring his matters ſo about that hee can take from you all feeling of your of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and all perceiuing and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the iudgement and vengeance of God, he wil ſuggeſt vnto you by the fleſh and the world diuers excuſes wherewith you may cloake and leſſen the ſame, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king you beléeue (if poſſibly he can) that it is not ſo horrible as men ſay it is: or els he will giue you his accuſtomed cuppe of ſlumbering, beſméered with ſome hope to returne to God againe, when the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny is ouerpaſt: but he will beware that he do not tel you, that all that which
<pb facs="tcp:21489:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> he doth, tendeth to draw you awaie by little &amp; little from the obedience of God your father, that he maie hale you to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall deſtruction: but on the contrarie he wil perſwade you, if he can, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you prouide for your good, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. Notwithſtanding you know that he is a lier and diſceiuer: for when he went about to blind the eies of our firſt pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, he told them: <hi>your eies ſhalbe opened:</hi> and when he ſought to make them deuils like to himſelfe, he ſaid vnto them, <hi>you ſhal be Gods:</hi> and intending to make them ſubiect to the firſt and ſecond death, he promiſed them immortalitie and life, ſaying: <hi>you ſhall not die.</hi> Beware then how you giue eare to his deceitfull and wicked counſels, to the inticements and inchauntments of this inchaunter, who is an enimie to your ſaluation: but rather hearken to the voice of that So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Phiſition who will not onelie make you feele and knowe your griefe, the daunger wherein you are, and the meanes whereby you maie prouide for your curing: but will alſo heale you him ſelfe, if your ſelues be not a ſtop and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance to it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21489:16"/>
            <p>Firſt of all then my brethren, I moſte earneſtlie beſeech, and beſeech you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the name of this great God and father of mercy, that you will earneſtlie conſider how many waies your fault de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth condemnation before God. You know that the moſt vile vice and that which both moſt of all deſerue to bee pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by all lawes both diuine and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, is this, to wit, if a childe do ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate that he withdraw himſelf from ſubmitting himſelfe to a good father and mother, yea denyeth them to be his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and doth become a ſeruaunt and ſlaue to a ſtraunger that is euen their verie deadly enimie, and in whoſe houſe he ſhall be conſtrayned to heare a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſpeeches tending to their diſhonor and reproche: or if a ſubiect bee ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull, vnfaithfull, diſloyall, and tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous to his natural Prince (at whoſe handes he had receiued manie benefites and great honour) as to reuolt from his obedience, and to band himſelfe with his mortall enimie which maketh open war againſt him. And yet you haue dealt thus. For the Lorde had ſometimes
<pb facs="tcp:21489:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> graunted you ſuch fauour as to drawe you out of Sathans family (whoſe ſlaues you were by nature) that he might adopt you in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, that hée might make you ſit at his own table, and traine you vp as his owne children, and make you inheritours of his kingdome, but you are departed out of his houſe, and hauing denyed him to bee your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you haue quite forſaken him, that you might become ſlaues to Sathan, in whoſe Synagoge your eares ſhall bée polluted with infinite and horrible blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies againſt the Maieſtie of God. You had a good mother, which is the Church of Ieſus Chriſt, which had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued you in her wombe by the incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible ſéede of the word of God, which had brought you forth not without great panges and thrals of afflictions and perſecutions, had giuen you ſucke with her two breaſts which are the olde and new teſtament, and which had brought you vp and nourſed you with great care, bearing your infirmities, and couering and wiping awaie your filth: and in lieu of all this you haue forſaken her, denying her to be your mother, and haue euen as
<pb facs="tcp:21489:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> it were throwne your ſelues into the armes of a ſtraunge ſtrumpet, or rather of that great whore of Babilon, which in ſtéed of giuing you good and wholeſome nouriſhment, giueth you to drinke the poiſon of her vncleannes and abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble whoredomes, that your ſoules maie thereby be infected and deſtroied: and ſhe ceaſeth not to make deadlie war againſt your chaſt mother the ſpouſe of Ieſus Chriſt, and to murther all her children. Furthermore, you had a good king and Soueraigne Lord euen Ieſus Chriſt the eternal ſonne of God, who loued you ſo dearelie that he gaue himſelfe vp to death for your ſakes which were his eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, who had deliuered you from the tirannie and ſlauerie of the deuill, who had redéemed you, not with gold or ſiluer or anie other corruptible thing, but by his own pretious bloud, which he ſhedde for you: and not onelie ſo, but had ouer and beſides graunted you ſo great honor as to make you his fellowes, that hee might make you partakers of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of his glorie, and of his celeſtial king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: and yet for all this, as ſoone as hee ſummoned you to the combate of the
<pb facs="tcp:21489:18"/> croſſe, that he might make you go the ſelfe ſame way which he had gone before you, to the ende that after the victorie hée might giue you the crowne of glorie and immortalitie: you turned your backes and forſooke him, yea you renounced him (if not al, at leaſt the greater part of you) by the moſt execrable abiuration which that infernall Dragon did euer ſpue out of his ſtinking mouth againſt the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of God: and that which more is, you haue inrolled your ſelues vnder the captaine of all impietie, which is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt of Rome, the ſworne enimie of the ſonne of God and of your ſaluation. Sée what an heape of backſlidinges, diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties, and moſt vile vnthankefulnes here is. But now I do wel perceiue that thoſe which will not giue glorie to God, nor giue eare to his worde, but take counſell of Sathan, to confirme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their errour, will not bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouided of replies, and will not bee aſhamed (ſome ſuch there bee) to ſéeke to couer or leſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their fault, alleadging that olde ſaying of time ſeruers and of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine backſliders, which knowe ful wel, yea in their hearts condemne the abuſes,
<pb facs="tcp:21489:18"/> impieties, ſuperſtitions, and Idolatries of Poperie, and are conſtrained to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the truth, to wit, that that is the verye true religion which we profeſſe through the grace of God. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding becauſe they are afraid to beare the blows, they will not march on vnder the banner of Ieſus Chriſt: but to the end they maye applye themſelues to the worlde, they follow the banner of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt. Moreouer if a man come to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh them and to tell them their due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, they replye, that albeit they ſerue the deuill with their bodies, yet they ceaſe not to be Chriſtians, and children of God, foraſmuch as they reſerue him the chiefe, which is the Spirite, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they ſerue and honour him: and though they haue forſaken the church of Ieſus Chriſt, and are fallen from their profeſſion of the Goſpell, and haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced religion, yet was not this in heart, and with affection, but onely in word. But all theſe allegations are ſo féeble, and theſe replies are ſo friuelous, that they deſerue none anſwere at all. And I am verie certaine that the moſte
<pb facs="tcp:21489:19"/> part of you my brethren, haue ſometimes reiected them, as not worthie to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and of none importaunce, when they would haue paied you with ſuch monie, yea I am ſure you laugh at them euen at this time in your owne hearts: and that for good cauſe. For where can you finde that the Lord hath permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs to make ſuch a partition between our ſoule and bodie, as with the one to ſerue God, and the deuill with the other? Is not the Lord the creatour and ſauiour aſwell of the one as of the other? Wil not he be glorified in both? We knowe that the Apoſtle will haue vs to offer not onelie our ſpirites, but alſo our bodies to the Lord in Sacrifice, that is, that we conſecrate and dedicate our ſelues to the ſeruice of God, both in ſoule and bodie. And that which more is, our bodies are called by the Apoſtle the Temples of God, and muſt be made partakers of his glorie aſwel as our ſelues: euen then when we ſhall be faſhioned according to the glorious bodie of the Sonne of God. It foloweth then that we muſt not ſerue the deuill therwith, polluting them with ſuperſtitions &amp; Idolatries, but we muſt
<pb facs="tcp:21489:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> kéepe them in al purenes and holines for the ſeruice of our god. For what huſband is he that is ſo fooliſh which would take ſuch an anſwere for paime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at his wiues hand, and that would ſuffer her to make ſuch a partition? If a woman were ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent and ſhameles as to ſpeake to her huſband on this wiſe: my huſband, I proſtitute my bodie indéed to ſuch &amp; ſuch, and make it common euerie daie in the brothelhouſe: but I reſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better part for you, and thats mine heart, wherwith I loue you, ſerue and honor you. I praie you, ſhould not ſuch a woman deſerue to be caſt off, of her huſband as a mocker, or rather as a common, vile, and deteſtable harlot? It is moſt certain that ſhe ſhould. What will the Lord then do, who is ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ouer his glorie and our ſaluation, who hath eſpouſed vs to himſelfe, that keeping our faith and promiſe made to him, wee maie bee pure and chaſt in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and mind? What will he do, (I ſay) if wee pollute our bodies in Idolatrie, which is ſpirituall whoredome? Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſee that this is a vaine excuſe: for indeede if this partition coulde haue beene made with a good conſcience,
<pb facs="tcp:21489:20"/> that is to ſaye, to proſtrate the bodie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Idols, and to keepe the heart for God, thinke wee that <hi>Daniell</hi> and the three Hebrue children would not rather haue vſed this opportunitie, then to haue expoſed their life to ſo great dangers, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there was nothing required at their hands ſaue onely an outward kinde of worſhip. But what ſhall we ſay of ſo manie martyrs, whoſe memorie is freſh as yet? Who would rather ſhed the laſt drop of their bloud, or bee burnt aliue with ſoft fire, then once to bowe their knée before <hi>Baal,</hi> howe little ſoeuer it were? Why did they it not for ſafegard of their life to preſerue it from ſo cruell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and from the fire? Becauſe they feared eternall torments, and the fire of Gods wrath, who abhorreth ſuch Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, what proteſtation ſoeuer wee make, that wee keepe our heart whole and pure for him, for he will haue both the one and the other. Now it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by that, what account we ought to make of that other replye, which manye amongſt you haue in their mouth, when a man ſtudieth to ſet before their eies the filthines of their fault. If I tel you that
<pb facs="tcp:21489:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> you haue abiured and forſworne chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an religion, and receiued and allowed al the abhominations of the great whore: alſo that you haue denyed the ſonne of God, and acknowledged this Idole of Antichriſt, putting him as it were in his place, you wil ſay that you did it not with your heart &amp; affection, but onely in word, to content men, and you thinke that you may eſcape by this goodly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction. But the Lord wil not iudge you after your ſubtilties &amp; ſophiſtrie, which ſhal vaniſh away like ſmoake, when we ſhall appeare before the throne of his Maieſtie. He hath not ſaid, Hee which ſhall confeſſe me with the heart and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, him wil I confeſſe before my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heauen, and before his Angels: &amp; he which ſhall deny me with the heart, him wil I alſo denie: but hee ſpeaketh of confeſſing and acknowledging thoſe which ſhal confeſſe him before men, and of reiecting and denying thoſe which ſhal haue denyed and renounced him before men: And what is it to confeſſe Ieſus Chriſt before men? It is to make open profeſſion of his Goſpel, to make frée co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his truth, yea to feele it with
<pb facs="tcp:21489:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> our bloud, if neede bee, after the example of this cloude of martyres, which ſhall ſtand vp in iudgment againſt you at the great daie. On the other ſide, what is it to denie Ieſus Chriſt before men? is it not to do euen as you haue done? And to do that which you do as yet dailie.</p>
            <p>But leaſt you thinke that I charge you to ſore, and without cauſe, I beſeech you conſider with an equall and quiet mind, what this curſed and deteſtable abiura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which you haue made, importeth: the which I cannot read without an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward trembling: eſpeciallie when I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the curſed and miſerable eſtate of ſo manie ſilie ſoules, which by this meanes are caught in Sathans net, wherein they continue intangled vntill ſuch time as they be vnited again with the Church of Ieſus Chriſt. But admit there be ſome few among you, which haue exempted themſelues from making the foreſaid ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuration, yet you ceaſe not to denie Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt to be your ſole Sauiour, to tread his bloud vnder your féete, and to renounce the merit of his death and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, when by your preſence &amp; aſſiſtance you approue that abhomination of the
<pb facs="tcp:21489:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> maſſe, which is the ſeale, and deteſtable ſacrament of this abiuration, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of the ſonne of God, and as it were a poiſoned heape of all the impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of popiſh doctrine.</p>
            <p>But for the better explaning of al this, let vs conſider the thinges more diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie: not that I purpoſe to rippe vp all the pointes that are compriſed in this good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie fourme of confeſſion and abiurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to refute them by reaſons and plaine teſtimonies of Scripture: for then I ſhould make a great volume touching that matter alone: which ſhould be a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous thing, ſeeing I ſhould then ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and do againe that which hath bene alreadie done moſt excellentlie by manie excellent ſeruants of God in our time: &amp; ſpeciallie by him who made not long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe, the anſwer to the profeſſion of faith, publiſhed againſt thoſe of the reformed church, by the Archbiſhop &amp; Munkes of <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> in which anſwere framed according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of god, he doth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie &amp; amplie depaint &amp; point out all the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes, impieties, ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; idolatries of poperie, which are gathered into their formes of abiuration, ſo that they are
<pb facs="tcp:21489:22"/> made knowne to al euen, to litle childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnleſſe they be ſuch as be blinded by the prince of darkenes. Furthermore I haue not interpriſed here to diſpute againſt thoſe, which admit no reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor no word of God, but only cuſtome, the traditions of the fathers, their opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, their dreams &amp; toyes, the lawes, ordinances, ſtatutes and tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nous decrées of their Antichriſt: for this were but loſt labour. And ſurely, I do not write properly to thoſe men: but vnto you my brethren do I ſpeak: to you I ſay, which know theſe abuſes by the word of God, which haue condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and deteſted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; which are conuict in your own conſcience, that al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pointes of doctrine contained in this abiuration, are as manye horrible blaſphemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Ieſus Chriſt, and the doctrine of his Goſpell: except the <hi>Nicene</hi> créed, the which theſe coſeners haue ſet in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beginning of this goodlye confeſſion, which they haue made, to bleare the eies of the ſimple fooles, as if their doctrine were conformable to this creede, and as if we did reiect and reproue the ſame: whereas contrariwiſe it is we that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it, confeſſe, and approue it in all
<pb facs="tcp:21489:22"/> points and throughout, as being groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the word of God: and on the other ſide they ſo pronounce it with their mouth in their execrable maſſe, that they reiect the moſt part of thoſe pointes that are contained in it, and in the Apoſtles créede: as wee coulde depaint out before their eies, and make them touch with their finger, if they had eies to ſee, eares to heare, and an heart to vnderſtand that which ſhoulde bee ſet before them out of the word of God. Foraſmuch then as you are not ignoraunt of theſe thinges which you haue learned out of the word of God, it ſhall bee inough for mee to touch them ſuperficially, to put you in minde thereof, and by this meanes to repreſent vnto you in ſome ſort, the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines, fowlenes, and deformitie of your fal, to the end you may be aſhamed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and confounded in your ſelues, yea ſo grieued, that God maye bee glorified in your conuerſion.</p>
            <p>Firſte of all, conſider I praye you howe manye impyeties and horrible blaſphemies are compriſed in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond article which foloweth immediatly after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> recitall of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Créed. You
<pb facs="tcp:21489:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> haue thereby proteſted to receiue and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, al the abuſes, errours, ſuperſtitions, idolatries, and abhominations of the Church of Rome, and to renounce the truth of God, which hath beene taught you out of his word: for you receiue the holie Scripture vpon ſuch condition, that it ſhall not be interpreted according to the Analogie of faith (as S. Paule co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, that it ſhal not be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted according to the Scripture it ſelf,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> conferring one place with an other, that there maie ſuch ſenſe be gathered thence as ſhalbe agréeable to the groundes and articles of the chriſtian faith: but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſenſe &amp; interpretation, which it ſhal pleaſe them to giue it, which falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taking to themſelues the right and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to interprete, do ordinarilie and moſt manifeſtlie corrupt and peruerte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame for maintenance of their dreames &amp; inuentions. So that by this one onlie ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle you haue promiſed to condemne (as being falſe) al the true and pure doctrine of your ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which you haue learned out of the word of God, interpreted by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God himſelfe: &amp; on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide to approue all the corruptions, lies, and
<pb facs="tcp:21489:23"/> falſhoode of the leauen of the Phariſies, which is in the doctrine of Antichriſt, And what ſhal we call this, but to turne light to darkneſſe, to reiect Ieſus Chriſt as a lier, and to embrace Antichriſt as being true? Surely by agréeing to this one onelie article, you haue (ſo much as in you laie) giuen as great aduantage to the enimies of the Goſpell, as if a man ſhould deliuer vp into the handes of his aduerſarie, all his papers, rightes, and inſtrumentes giuing him leaue to turne them all to his moſt aduantage, yea to interprete the lawes as he liſt, and to pronounce ſuch ſentence as he ſhal think good, as if he were both iudge &amp; plaintiffe. And ſurely there is no errour ſo abſurd, no abuſe ſo groſſe, no impietie ſo abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, which Antichriſt and his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters doe not maintaine by this meanes againſt the trueth of God: for when a man ſhall alleadge plaine places of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in defence of the trueth, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute falſhood: and that the matter ſhall be made ſo plain and ſo euident of it ſelf, that they cannot tell what to anſweare on the contrarie, this ſhal be their laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge: to wit, that our holie mother the
<pb facs="tcp:21489:24"/> church vnderſtandeth theſe places other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: and that the Scripture admitteth none other ſenſe and interpretation, no yet any other authority, ſaue that which it pleaſeth our holie father the Pope to beſtow vpon it. Thus wil they argue: ſo that by making you allow and approue this article, there reſteth no more now, but that they may fréely triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ph ouer Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and his doctrine, in ſo much that it was not néedful to ſpecifie the reſt which follow: the proofe whereof depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon the graunting of this alone. Notwithſtanding ſéeing that to the ende they might more ſtrictly binde you vnto them they make a recital of the principal heads of their falſe doctrine examine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al one after another, and you ſhal ful wel know what reprehenſion your back ſliding deſerueth.</p>
            <p>The third is no leſſe pernicious tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond. For it foloweth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it as a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral conſequence, drawing after it al the ſpecial conſequences &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſions, which they make touching their inuentions, &amp; humane traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, wherby they haue cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupted &amp; peruerted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pure ſeruice of God aſwel in regard of the doctrine, as of the
<pb facs="tcp:21489:24"/> ceremonies, which they coulde neuer maintain &amp; defend, were it not that their falſe gloſes &amp; interpretations which they giue vpon the ſcriptures did help them. Wherefore ſeing you haue graunted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this, that it belongeth to them to giue the Scripture ſuch ſenſe and interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as ſhal ſéeme beſt to them, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth therevpon, that you do likewiſe graunt to them, that al the abuſes, al the dreames, and toies, al the ceremonies &amp; obſeruations which Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath brought in into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, wherof ſome are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fooliſh, friuolous, &amp; ridiculous, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuperſtitious coupled together with impiety &amp; idolatry, without hauing any ground in the ſcripture, yea being direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary to the ſame for the moſt part, and by the which alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puritie and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religion hath bin tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a kind of Iudaiſm &amp; Paganiſm: you graunt to them, I ſay, that al theſe bables, al this filth &amp; abhominations are good and holie, as being parcels of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God, being eſtabliſhed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church by our Lord Ieſus Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles: as alſo theſe lyers haue bin ſo ſhameleſſe as to cal al theſe filthy and ſtinking
<pb facs="tcp:21489:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> dregs, which haue infected the Church: traditions, obſeruations, and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Apoſtles. But you know full wel that they agrée aſwell with the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles, as dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes with light, and falſhood with truth. For where can they finde that Ieſus Chriſt or his Apoſtles did ordain y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe together with the furniture &amp; trappings thereof which are full of fooliſhe toies? Wher can they finde that filth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they haue corrupted holie baptiſm, as creame, ſalt, ſpittle, coniured water, lights and ſuch like thinges? Where ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they finde the baptizing of Belles, holie water, Proceſſions, Praier for the dead, and a thouſand ſuch bables, toies, &amp; tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles as were too long to rehearſe? But chieflie an infinite number of errors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the maſſe, and in al the reſt of their booke of ceremonies? Of which ſort is that execrable idolatrie which they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit in worſhipping a morſell of Bread, the inuocation and interceſſion of ſaints the adoring and worſhipping of the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and reliques of dead Saints, the fire of Purgatorie, the Popes pardons &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, and ſuch like impieties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb facs="tcp:21489:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> by the worde of God. And yet for al this like ſéelie ſoules you haue mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerablie bound your ſelues to receiue and approue al theſe thinges. O eternal God is it poſſible that you ſhould haue bin ſo vndiſcrete? Is it poſſible that you ſhould continue ſo blockiſh as to haue no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe of conſcience in you.</p>
            <p>But let vs procéede: you haue béene taught out of the word of God that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt hath for the continuall vſe of his Church inſtituted onelie two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to wit, Baptiſme, and the holie Supper, to repreſent vnto vs the holie myſteries of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is to ſaie, our regeneration, and the ſpirituall life which we drawe from Ieſus Chriſt our head, in as much as wée are moſt ſtrictly vnited and coupled together with him: and to ſeale vp in our heartes the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of ſaluation and eternal life, which are there made vnto vs by the Lorde. You know moreouer, that the Church of God muſt content it ſelf with theſe two, not onelie becauſe they are ſufficient to repreſent vnto vs all the benefites of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and to aſſure vs of his grace &amp; fauour, but alſo becauſe it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb facs="tcp:21489:26"/> for mortal ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, no not for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verie An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels to ordaine any ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, or to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh any thing in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruice of God: foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as this right belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth to god alone. Notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding mark what you confeſſe by the fourth article of this tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nous ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuration: you ackowledge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there bee 7. ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in the law of grace, inſtituted by Ieſus Chriſt: which is moſt falſe. We confeſſe indéed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that which they cal Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation (which is nothing els but a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceuing of ſuch as are inſtructed &amp; catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church catechiſms into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, of thoſe which hauing bin ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſed and inſtructed in the doctrine of Chriſt, were receiued into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> felowſhip of the faithful with praier to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to God) is an holy thing, which hath bin practiſed in the Primitiue Church, euen in the Apoſtles time: alſo we do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but that repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (which is nothing elſe but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> acknowledging of our faults &amp; the miſliking of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, &amp; the ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dment of our life) is a good &amp; wholſome thing, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded of God: we confeſſe alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that which they cal the order of Prieſthoode (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, the laying on of hands, which was vſed in the Church in
<pb facs="tcp:21489:26"/> old time, &amp; which is vſed at this daye in many reformed Churches, when Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, Elders, Deacons, &amp; other eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical perſons are to be admitted vnto the publike charges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church) we confeſſe, I ſay, that this is a laudable &amp; holy cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, ordained &amp; practiſed by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. As for marriage we know alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is an holie inſtitution of the Lord, &amp; that the cuſtome of bleſſing the ſame in the Church is Chriſtian. We graunt I ſay, that al theſe things are good and holy, &amp; are grounded vppon the worde of God: but we deny them to be Sacramentes. Firſt of al becauſe Ieſus Chriſt hath not inſtituted them to be ſuche: and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie becauſe they haue not thoſe thinges that are required neceſſarily in true Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments: for then they muſt haue been ordayned by Ieſus Chriſt to continue in the Church vntill the conſummation of the worlde: and for the vſe of the whole Churche in generall, and of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie member thereof in particular. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, there ſhoulde haue beene vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſignes to repreſent the inuiſible graces of God, and the promiſes of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and eternal life, which things we
<pb facs="tcp:21489:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſée to be in baptiſme and in the holie ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per onelie. As for extreame vnction as they cal it, we doe not denie but that the oile wherewith the Apoſtles did annoint the ſicke, was an outward ſigne which did repreſent the grace of God, euen in that time of the ſaid Apoſtles who had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gift of healing: but this Sacrament la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted but for a time, and had an ende toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the gift of healing &amp; working miracles. We conclude then that there be but two Sacraments in the Church of Chriſt, and that the other fiue were inuented by men. And yet you confeſſe that al that was inſtituted by Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: &amp; that which is worſe, you auouch an horrible blaſphemie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you graunt that the Sacraments conferre grace: for by this you attribute not onelie to the true Sacramentes, but alſo to mens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, that which belongeth to the holie Ghoſt, who alone conferreth the grace ſignified by them, and that to the true faithfull alone. And the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts (as alſo the word) are onelie inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which he vſeth to this end: ſo that we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by them nothing appertaining to our ſaluation, vnleſſe the ſpirite of God
<pb facs="tcp:21489:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> worke inwardly in vs, and vnleſſe wée haue a true and liuely faith.</p>
            <p>You haue alſo learned by the ſame word of God that the ſaid Sacramentes muſt be miniſtred with the ſame puritie &amp; ſimplicity wherwith they were inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our ſoueraigne Doctor &amp; maiſter Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Deut 4. &amp; 12. Pro. 30. Apo. 22.</note> and that it is an intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble boldnes to adde any thing therto, and deteſtable ſacrilege to take any thing, therfro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how litle ſoeuer it be: foraſmuch as this were to ſéek to be more wiſe than he who is the eternal wiſedome of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And yet neuertheleſſe you approue by the firſt article all thoſe ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies which theſe men haue annexed to the adminiſtration of the Sacraments, which they haue wickedly and vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profaned and polluted. Alſo you allow al thoſe things which they vſe in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration thereof, which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue inuented and ordained how fooliſhe, ſuperſtitious and wicked ſoeuer they be: as you know that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more part of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do rather reſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble iuglers trickes and toies, or the ſuperſtitious &amp; prophane fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heathen, then the ſimplicity &amp; grauity of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Moreouer, you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue
<pb facs="tcp:21489:28"/> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame article two horrible ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crileges which amongeſt others they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to wit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſeparate thoſe thinges which God hath coupled togither, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the worde, which is as it were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoul of the ſacraments: and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they rent in péeces the holie Supper of the Lord, if that which they cal their Communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be the true ſupper: for they exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municat the ſimple people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one eſſential part of the ſupper, namelie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cup, contrarie to the expreſſe commandement of Ieſus Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>Drinke ye all of this.</hi> And it is ſaid in another of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſts, that all of them dranke thereof.<note place="margin">Mat. 26. Mar. 14.</note> Conſider then with what conſcience you could aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to ſuch falſhoods and iniquities.</p>
            <p>But this is not al: come to that which followeth afterwarde, &amp; conſider I praie you how many pernicious errors, &amp; hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible blaſphemies are contained in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſixt and ſeuenth articles. Firſt of al you haue béene taught by the woorde of God that all hope of our ſaluation reſteth in the onlie oblation which Ieſus Chriſt made of his bodie vppon the croſſe to appeaſe the wrath of God towarde his elect,
<pb facs="tcp:21489:28"/> &amp; that this ſacrifice of the ſonne of God was once ſo offered,<note place="margin">Heb. 7. &amp; 9.</note> as ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, that it neither can nor ought to bée reiterated, béeing moſt intire and perfect and therefore moſt ſufficient to reconcile vs to God. Notwithſtanding you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce this, or at leaſt ſeeme to make it imperfect and inſufficient, when you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that the maſſe is a propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie ſacrifice for the quick and the dead, that is to ſaie, that it is of ſuche power as to purchaſe Gods fauour, to appeaſe his wrath, and to make ſatiſfaction for ſinnes, and in ſumme to redeem and ſaue vs: ſo that you put the maſſe an execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble idol in place of Ieſus Chriſt, ſpoiling him of the honor which to him belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth, which is to be our ſole &amp; ſoueraign prieſt, and onlie propitiatory ſacrifice which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone hath this vertue to appeaſe the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; to make him become fauorable to vs. Furthermore you auouch an horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble blaſphemie againſt the manhood of Ieſus Chriſt, when you confeſſe this goodly doctrine of their tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And ſurely this errour is of ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, that it bringeth w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> it an infinit number of other errours, and ſpoyleth
<pb facs="tcp:21489:29"/> vs of al hope of ſaluation, if we receiue it. For if Ieſus Chriſt were not verie man, he ſhoulde not haue truelie died for vs, and ſo haue ſatiſfied Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the ſinnes of men, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently we ſhould as yet remaine in death. But now he ſhould not haue bin verie man like to vs in al thinges except ſinne,<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 2. &amp; 4.</note> as ſaith the Apoſtle, if his body had béene inuiſible as ſome ghoſt, vnder a morcell of bread at ſuch time as hee or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained his Supper together with his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles: and if the Bread and Wine were tranſubſtantiated into his bodie and into his blood, by whiſpering cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine woordes, which they call Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental woordes (which is a kinde of charme) ſo that hee was there fleſhe and bone, as thicke and as great as when hée was vpon the true trée of the croſſe, as theſe men moſt impudently affirme: it ſhould folow that the wicked ones &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleuing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world coulde receiue Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; that he ſhould be in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to be gnawn of vermin, not to ſpeak of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand other errors &amp; da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable abſurdities which ſhould require too long time if I ſhould ſtande to rip the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp. Alſo if Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:21489:29"/> Chriſt ſhould euery day come down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the Prieſts hands, that which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> articles of our faith ſhould not be true, that he is aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where he ſhal be (as touching his huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity) vntil he come at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt day to iudge both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quick &amp; the dead: as is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by S. <hi>Peter,</hi> who ſaith <hi>that the heauens muſt containe him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 3.</note> 
               <hi>vntil the reſtoring of al things, &amp;c.</hi> Furthermore if he wer at one time in an infinite number of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as touching his humanitye, his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature ſhuld be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature which alone is infinite. To be ſhort, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſts touching the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hood of Ieſus Chriſt were true, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were he not very man, &amp; ſo conſequently not our mediator. And if this were ſo, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſholud it folow that we ſhould be as yet vnder the curſe of God. Marke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what you haue done. But ouer and beſides co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that by allowing that doctrine of tranſubſtantiation, you make your ſelfe as guilty of that curſed idolatry which is committed in worſhipping a morſell of paſte or bread, as if it were the ſonne of God. I omit to ſpeake of another errour which iſſueth out of their tranſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:21489:30"/> wherof they make mention about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of the ſeuenth article: where they ſay that vnder both kindes is wholly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned the body of Ieſus Chriſt. They had forgotten to ſaie the blood, that they might thereby continue their concomita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or accompanying of both kinds vnder one, which they haue forged in their own brain, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end they might maintain this ſacrilege, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue robbed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimple people of the vſe of the cup. But there is not in al that ſo much as one ſparkle of truth, and yet you allow all theſe iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by this curſed abiuration.</p>
            <p>As for Purgatorie which you confeſſe in the eight article, doe you not perceiue what violence you offer to the ſonne of God,<note place="margin">Iohn 1. 1. Ioh. 1. 1. Ioh. 2. Heb. 1.</note> and what iniurie you offer to your ſelues? You know that Ieſus Chriſt is that Lambe of God which taketh awaie the ſinnes of the world: that his bloud cleanſeth vs from all ſinne: that he is the attonement or propitiaton for our ſins, &amp; that he hmſelfe hath purged them, &amp;c. Lo it is he which is our true Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. And yet you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe another, making of none effect, ſo much as in you lieth, the vertue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precious blood of this vnſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:21489:30"/> lambe, and renouncing the true pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of your ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Furthermore,<note place="margin">Mat. 4. Ioh. 14. Ioh. 15. 1. tim 2. 1. Ioh. 2.</note> know you not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is one onelie God whom we muſt worſhip and reuerence, to whom we muſt pray, &amp; vppon whom we muſt call, and that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name and mediation of Ieſus Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone who is our onelie mediatour, aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and interceſſour? And yet conſider what confeſſion you haue made in the ninth Article contrarie to your owne conſcience: that is, that you muſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, praie vnto, and call vpon Saintes: which is manifeſt idolatry, foraſmuch as inuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a kind of worſhipping. And furthermore you auouch that the ſaints are our aduocates &amp; interceſſors, which is to robbe Ieſus Chriſt of that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which belongeth to him alone. But you doe woorſe then this comes too, when you confeſſe that you muſt woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe or reuerence the reliques of the ſaide Saintes: vnder which woordes they comprehende not onelie the bones and reliques of dead Saintes, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the ſtinking and rotten carkaiſes of manie, whoſe ſoules it maie be are tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in Hell, as ſaieth an auncient
<pb facs="tcp:21489:31"/> Doctor? and not onely the bones of men, but alſo of beaſts, which theſe deceiuers make the poore blockiſh people worſhip, that they may thereby get money. And is it poſſible the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that you ſhould be come to ſuch blockiſhnes?</p>
            <p>But what wil you ſay to that which they make you confeſſe by the tenth arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle? that men muſt not onlie haue images of Ieſus Chriſt, of the virgin Marie, and of al the other ſaints, but alſo that they muſt worſhip and honor the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Know you not that this is contrarie to the expreſſe commandement of the Lorde? and that ſuch honour and worſhip is abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble idolatrie?<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> Moreouer, haue you ſo ſlenderly profited in the knowledge of God, and of his holy truth, that you haue not learned to abhor and deteſt that cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and damnable merchaundize which the Pope maketh of his pardons and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, which he ſelleth for good rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſummes of readie money, to the greate diſhonour of the ſonne of God, to the contempt of his precious bloud, and to the hurte of poore ſoules? Haue you euer read eyther in the olde or newe Teſtament, that the bloud and
<pb facs="tcp:21489:31"/> merites of Saintes ought to be coupled with the bloud and merit of Ieſus Chriſt thereby to race out ſinnes, and to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Gods iuſtice. Haue you euer read that Ieſus Chriſt hath commaunded that of ſuch a mingle mangle ſhould be made a treaſure which ſhould be at the diſpoſing of that Antichriſt of Rome, to beſtow it vpon whom ſoeuer he will, or rather to ſell it to thoſe, that woulde buye it, and that ſuch pardons ſhoulde bee profitable for all Chriſtians, that is to ſay, ſuch as ſhould be able to ſaue them from ſinne and from eternall death. And yet they are ſo impudent as to ſaye ſo, yea to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that Ieſus Chriſt is the authour of ſuch abhominations, &amp; that hath he left them to the church, that is according to their interpretation, to the Pope, that he might be the kéeper and ſteward there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And yet you haue bene ſo blinde as to graunt ſuch an impietie by the eleuenth article. O immortal God, who would e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue looked for anie ſuch thinge at your hands.</p>
            <p>And that which worſe is, you do not onely approue this curſed tyrannie of Antichriſt, confeſſing by the twelfth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle
<pb facs="tcp:21489:32"/> that the great whore of Babilon (which they falſelie call the holie Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike and Apoſtolike Church) is the mother and miſtreſſe of all other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but you do alſo withdraw your ſelues from the obedience and ſubiection which you owe vnto the onlie, and high Biſhop of our ſoules, which is Ieſus Chriſt, that you maie become ſlaues and ſeruants to the tyrannous lordſhip of the Biſhop of Rome, (yea binding your ſelues with promiſe and oth therto) who calleth himſelfe moſt impudentlie the ſucceſſour of Peter. But you know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the life and doctrine of thone and other, doe plainelie ſhew that there is as great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwéene S. Peter and the pope of Rome, as betwéene an Angell of God, and an angell of Sathan. Which were quickly proued, if it were néedfull to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter anie farther into this matter: as alſo that which he ſaith of this holie Apoſtle, calling him Prince or chiefe of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, to the end he maie eſtabliſh his own tyranous primacie. But you know that this is a faire flat lye: for he cannot finde ſo much as one ſillable in the whole ſcripture, whereby he can proue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:21489:32"/> Chriſt appointed Peter to be prince and chiefe ouer his other Apoſtles much leſſe that this holie Apoſtle did euer exerciſe anie lordſhip ouer his companions: but rather we ſee that all of them did faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully exerciſe their miniſterie there wher God called them, with equall athoritie, without anie pretence of primacie or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie of one ouer another. But ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit we ſhould graunt the Pope that, yet he muſt proue manie other thinges before he can make this concluſion, that he is therefore chiefe of all Biſhops, and head of the Church. Which hee ſhall neuer be able to do out of the word of God. You are not ignorant how vntru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this curſed creature calleth himſelfe the vicar of Ieſus Chriſt: who ceaſeth not to perſecute him in his members with deſperate rage: yea who hath cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, peruerted, and falſifyed the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Goſpell: who oppreſſeth the Church of Ieſus Chriſt, conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning her with might and main to forſake and renounce her true ſpouſe, to commit fornication with Satan in all maner of pollutions, profanations, &amp; abhominable idolatries, that he may hale her headlong
<pb facs="tcp:21489:33"/> with him to hell. You know that hee is the man of ſinne, the ſonne of perdition, which ſitteth in the temple of God, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelfe againſt God, and making himſelfe to be worſhipped as God: yea boaſting and vanting himſelfe forth as God: you know that he is in ſumme ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Antichriſt, that is, a ſworne enimye of Ieſus Chriſt and his doctrine. To bee briefe, you knowe that hee is the verie lieutenant and vicar of that murtherer of bodies and ſoules, which is the deuill: whoſe commandements and ordinances he executeth moſt exactly againſt the poore faithfull children of God: and yet you are ſo beſotted that you confeſſe him to be the vicar of Ieſus Chriſt. O what blindnes is this? And what brutiſh bloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſhnes.</p>
            <p>Finally, to the ende you might leaue nothing vndone which might appertain to a full and perfect renouncing of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion, of the fellowſhip of Ieſus Chriſt and of his church, and to a full ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation and acknowledging of all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties and abhominations which are in the kingdome of Antichriſt, you promiſe and vow to keepe intirely and inuiola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie
<pb facs="tcp:21489:33"/> euen vntill your laſt breat all that which hath bene determined and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by their Canons, decrees, and councels, and principally all the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and wicked decrées and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the councell of Trent: wherein the pure and true doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt hath bene accurſed and condemned as falſe and erronious: and contrariwiſe wherein all the impieties and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Antichrtſt haue beene confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and ratified: and all this without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie hearing of the matter, and without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie deciding of anie by the word of God: but onely vpon a certaine abſolute and tyrannous authoritie, as appeareth by the articles of the ſaid Councell. This is in ſumme that euill and offence which you haue committed againſt God and your owne ſaluation by this wicked and diueliſh confeſſion and abiuration: there is ſome difference betwéene that which was imprinted at Lyons, which I haue followed, and that which is imprinted at Paris: firſt in that the order of the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and third articles is chaunged: and alſo in that which is imprinted at Paris, there be two other errors, the one touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:21489:34"/> frée will, and the other touching iuſtification by workes: vpon refutation whereof, I wil not ſtand anie longer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well aſſured that you condemne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aſwel as all the reſt. And therefore you are ſo much the more blame worthie in that you auouch them contrarie to your owne conſcience. Conſider then my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren into what a danger of deſtruction you haue throwen your ſelues headlong, and how ſhameful, cowardly, and vile your renouncing whereby you haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of the goſpel, is, ſo to returne to thoſe corruptions which you had before caſt vp, and to welter againe in that filthie mire from which you were once waſhed. Open your eies, and behold how great the foulenes and filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of your fault is. Surely the more I conſider the ſame, together with all the circumſtances thereof, the more damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble do I find it to be both before God and alſo before men: for it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehendeth in it an infinite number of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt monſtrous crimes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> coulde be committed againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maieſtie of God. You may iudge of it as you ſhal think good, but it is ſo: you know how greatly wee are bound to loue him,
<pb facs="tcp:21489:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> who hath ſo dearly loued vs that he hath (as one would ſaie) forgotten himſelf, to ſaue vs, and to bring vs from that curſed and miſerable eſtate wherein wee ſtood through our owne fault. Hee hath not ſpared his onlie and welbeloued ſonne, but hath deliuered him vp to death, yea euen to the death of the croſſe, for vs that were his enimies: the ſonne alſo for his part, who would haue thought it no rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie to make himſelfe equall with God, (as ſaith the Apoſtle) did notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding abaſe himſelf ful low that he might lift vs vp on high,<note place="margin">Phi. 2.</note> he became poore to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich vs, he couered himſelfe with our confuſion and ſhame that he might make vs partakers of his glorie, hee became mortall, that we might haue immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: to be ſhort, he put himſelfe in our place, he preſented him ſelfe giltie before Gods iudgement ſeate, and deſcended into hell that he might bring vs thence and exalte vs to the heauenlye inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce. Nowe then ought not this infinite bountie, this incomparable loue, this incomprehenſible fauour, this deapth of compaſſions and mercies, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame vs with a mutual loue toward our
<pb facs="tcp:21489:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> good God, and toward his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt. And what doth this loue import, ſaue onely that being dedicated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to his ſeruice, we ſhould glorifie him in all and through all thinges, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring his honour and glorie, the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of his name, the aduauncement of his kingdome, the feare, the reuerence, and the obedience which wee owe vnto him, before all thinges that are pleaſant to the eye, good, precious, and excellent in this world, yea euen before our verie life it ſelfe. But marke I pray you how you haue done your duetie in this point. You haue preferred the loue of the world and of your ſelues before the loue of god: you haue diſhonoured and defamed the Lord (ſo much as in you lyeth) a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand thouſand waies. For ouer and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that you haue infringed and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken his couenant, you haue denyed him to be your God and father, you haue ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured his holy and ſacred truth, you haue allowed and receiued in ſtéede of it that which is falſehood, you haue denyed the ſonne of God, and taken Antichriſt for your head, you haue polluted your bodies (which he had choſen to be his temple)
<pb facs="tcp:21489:35"/> by abhominable idolatry, you haue made the holy ghoſt, and the holy Angels hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie and ſorrowful, and grieued the whole Church of God, which is aſhamed and confounded by reaſon of your backſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and euen ſobbeth and lamenteth for the ſame: beſides all theſe euils, I ſaye, there is this alſo, that is, that nowe you open the mouth of the vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing to blaſpheme (more then euer heretofore) the holie and pretious name of God whereon you ſometimes called. Knowe you not with what floutes, ſcoffes, and ſcornes worldly and profane men were wont vnreuerently to ſpeake of Chriſtian religion, euen then when they had but ſmall occaſion? But nowe how great occaſion do you miniſter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them by your backſliding? Will not they ſay that the religion whereof you made profeſſion, is not ſo good, ſo true, nor ſo well grounded vpon the word of God, as you haue profeſſed? Will not they ſpeake euill of the doctrine of the Goſpell, yea and of Ieſus Chriſte him ſelfe, as if you had beene deceiued by him? Sathan, Antichriſte, and all his miniſters, as the Prieſtes,
<pb facs="tcp:21489:36"/> munkes, and al that rabble which fight for their bellies againſt the truth of god, al theſe I ſaye will make bone fires for ioy, will laugh with wide open mouth, will triumph, and depreſſe the true doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Ieſus Chriſt, and extoll their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, ſuperſtitions, and idolatries.</p>
            <p>In like maner you are the cauſe that the Lord ſhal be blaſphemed and diſfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that religion ſhall bee deſpiſed and not regarded, that the doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt ſhal be mocked and ſcorned, and that the enimies ſhal ſet vp their hornes on high, and triumph concerning the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie which they thinke they haue got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
            <p>And that which more is, you let and hinder ſo much as in you lyeth, the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Ieſus Chriſt: for if you woulde haue done your duetie, and haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantlye perſiſted in the profeſſion and confeſſion of the Goſpel, if you had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred (as you ought) the honor and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God, and your owne ſaluation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your goods, pleaſures, and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, before the honour of the worlde, of your ſelues, and of your neighbours, and before your owne life, many ſhould haue
<pb facs="tcp:21489:36"/> bene wel edified thereby, whereas nowe they are greatlie offended and grieued by your fall: thoſe that are ſtraungers from the knowledge of Ieſus Chriſte, would haue bene brought nigh vnto him to taſt of the doctrine of the goſpel, if you would haue ſtood to the defenſe thereof, though it had bin with loſſe of your goods and liues: as in times paſt the holie mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres wan more ſoules to Ieſus Chriſt by their inuincible conſtancie, then by their doctrine and inſtruction. But nowe thoſe that neuer taſted of the ſame, will more loath it then euer, ſeing you make leſſe account of it then Eſau did of his Birthright, who ſold it for one meſſe of pottage. Thoſe which began to diſcouer the abuſes, ſuperſtitions, and idolatries, of poperie, and to haue ſome ſmel of the Goſpel, would haue gone forward, and would haue bene confirmed by your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance: but now ſeing you forſake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to loue, they wil alſo be out of liking w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame: &amp; on the other ſide, ſeeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you receiue againe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to diſdaine, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their falſe opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> becom athiſts. You know that in the church of
<pb facs="tcp:21489:37"/> God there be manie which make profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſtian religion, and yet there is in them great infirmitie, whereof Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt will haue vs to haue regarde that we do not offend them: theſe would haue beene fortified and ſtrengthned by your good example: but when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore ſimple people which had but ſlenderlye profited and which had béene but ſimplye inſtructed, ſaw that manie of you which had attained to ſo great honour as to bée called to publike charges of the Church, or which were otherwiſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; ſuch as were had in great reputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, &amp; which were reputed as torches and lanternes to giue light to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: I ſay when the poore ſimple peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which were but weake, ſaw you ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally turne your backes ſo cowardlye, ſurely it was vnto them marueilous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue, &amp; a very great diſcouragement: ſo that a great many did yéeld when they were tried, and fel through your occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And ſurely it is no thankes to you that all of them did not the like: for ſurelye I will ſpeake this to your ſhame, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny amongſt you haue bene ſo miſerable and curſed, as to be Sathans to others,
<pb facs="tcp:21489:37"/> tempting and pricking them forward to do as you did: O curſed wretches, was it not inough for you to deſtroy your ſelues vnleſſe you muſt alſo become giltie of the deſtruction and ruine of your poore brethren? And now aſſuredly you are ſuch, if you and they die in this eſtate.</p>
            <p>You oppoſe your ſelues yet after another ſort againſt the aduauncement of Gods glorie, and of the kingdome of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, yea you hinder it ſo much as in you lyeth: for you haue done what you can to ſpoyle the the poore church of Ieſus Chriſt of Paſtors: foraſmuch as you do not only gréeue them, but alſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour and diſfame them: ſo that they muſt néeds be aſhamed &amp; confounded by meanes of you. For ſéeing you do ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably and cowardly reuolt from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion, and renounce the truth of god which they haue preached vnto you, do you not ſecretly or rather openly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you count the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as falſe prophets &amp; ſeducers, which haue deceiued you, &amp; fed you with lyes? Now God is witnes, &amp; your owne conſcience doth reproue you of the contrarie. But notwithſtanding ſéeing their hope to bee fruſtrate, &amp; that
<pb facs="tcp:21489:38"/> they are ſo ſimply rewarded at your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds for their paines, yea y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue euil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paied vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for good, ſhal not this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them from imploying the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues hereafter about the worke of your ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Aſſuredly, if they had not greater regard to the glory of God, then to your vnthankfulnes, &amp; if they were not more deſirous of your ſaluation then you your ſelues, they would quite giue ouer all: &amp; it may be there will be ſome that will do ſo indéed: &amp; alſo many young men which would haue dedicated themſelues to the ſtudie of diuinitie, that they might ſerue in the miniſtrie, will begin to loath the ſame through your fault. So that it is to be feared that it will come to paſſe that there will very few be found which will till and ſow in ſuch euill ground wherof they ſhall reape ſo ſmall fruites. And what can we expect from y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> but beaſtly &amp; brutiſh ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſuch as was ſometimes and is as yet in poperie: corruption of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pure ſeruice of God, and finally miſerable deſolation? Now the Lord wil not leaue of to finiſh his worke, and to ſend labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers into his harueſt, when hee ſhall ſée time. Yet ſo it is that you ſhall neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:21489:38"/> be alwaies giltie of the foreſaide euils, in as much as they be fruites and effects of your cowardlines and vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, howſoeuer the Lorde do turne them to ſome other end, by his infinite goodnes.</p>
            <p>You ſée then howe manye monſtrous crimes are coupled with your fault &amp; fal: but yet this is not al, for there be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of other ſins that depende thereupon: whereof I touch only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt notorious, and that without vſing anye great diſcourſes and amplifications (as néed doth require) that I may paint out the ſame vnto you: for I content my ſelf with ſetting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> down only, for auoiding prolixitie. Notwithſtanding it ſtandeth you vpon to thinke vpon them, and to weigh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wel, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you may be brought to deteſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: otherwiſe they ſhal be ordered before your face in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great day of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord. Conſider then I pray you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ouer and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that which hath bene touched here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, you haue committed and do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch an euill as is no ſmal one: for by your backſlyding you condemne not only thoſe which ſtand as yet at this day through the grace of God in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb facs="tcp:21489:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> &amp; confeſſion of the Goſpell, as if they were fooles and ſenſeles, or els mad men, but you doe alſo condemne all thoſe which are dead in our Lord: and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally a great number of the faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God and of holy martyres, who haue ſealed with their owne bloud that doctrine which you haue abiured, and which did chooſe rather to looſe their goods, honours, and other commodities of this life: to be baniſhed and chaſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their owne houſes, to be depriued of their fathers, mothers, wiues, children kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke &amp; frends: to be caſt in priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt ſerpents and toades: to be bound &amp; chai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, beaten, railed vpon, racked and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by tormentors, and to ſuffer all manner cruelties and torments: yea they choſe rather to die the moſt cruel deaths y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> could be inuented, then to pollute them ſelues in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuperſtitions &amp; idolatries of poperie, which you allowe now by your reuolting, &amp; do miſerably defile both your ſoules, &amp; alſo your bodies. You condemne all thoſe I ſaye, as if they had bene vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcréete men, or ſome wicked heretikes: &amp; on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrarie you iuſtify y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> carnal and tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nous barbariſme of tyrants &amp; perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors,
<pb facs="tcp:21489:39"/> of vniuſt iudges, and cruel torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors who haue murthered and put them to death. And yet your owne conſcience telleth you that they ſuffered for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes ſake, and gaue their liues for the name of Ieſus Chriſt: and that they are therefore bleſſed, as Ieſus Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth them to be. On the other ſide, that thoſe which put them to death are accurſed, vnhappie, and deteſtable, yea very inſtrumentes of Satan, for whom there is prepared an horrible iudgement, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vengeance of God, which they ſhal not eſcape, howſoeuer it be long a comming. Therefore you are ſo muche the more without excuſe before God, ſéeing that you condemne thoſe whom you know to be iuſt and innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and approue and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie thoſe whom you know to bee wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vngodly. He which condemneth the iuſt, and iuſtifieth the wicked, they are both alike abhominable before the Lorde, ſaith <hi>Salomon.</hi> If you ſaie that you intende no ſuch thing: you ſaie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing touching this matter which I doe not willingly beleeue: but I aunſwere alſo, that the Lorde doth not iudge men according to their intentions, if they bée
<pb facs="tcp:21489:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> not ruled according to his worde. Know you then that that which you haue done and do as yet, ſo long as you continue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolts, maketh you guiltie of al the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood which hath bin ſhed vntil this day by the executioners and Souldiers of Satan and of Antichriſt, and of al the iniuries and outrages which the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of GOD and of his trueth haue committed, and doe as yet committe dailie againſt the poore members of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: who cannot but count you his enemies ſo long as you are on their ſide which make warre againſt him.</p>
            <p>What anſwere will you make to all theſe points, when you ſhal appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the iudgement ſeat of God? What excuſes will you make? It maie be you wil ſay, that that which you did was not done with a glad heart, and of ſet pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as if you did approue Poperie, and that you did intend to liue and die in it, or as if you did condemne that Religion which onlie you acknowledge to be good, holie and approued of God, wherevnto alſo you deſire to returne in time, by the grace of GOD, but that you did it one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="tcp:21489:40"/> to eſcape the violence of this outrage which came vpon you vnawares. That is as much as if you ſhould ſaie, that you were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained ſomwhat to faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſelues after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, to beare off y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blows &amp; to ſaue your goodes and honours, your ſelues, your wiues, &amp; children &amp;c. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome will make manie excuſes, ſaying: I had a charge and familie, I knowe no waie nor meanes how to eſcape out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme, I know not whither to go to get my liuing, &amp; to prouide for the neceſſities of theſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are mine: the time which was troubleſome, the inſtance and importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natneſſe of my kinſfolkes &amp; friendes, the teares of my wife, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cries of my childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; other trials did ſo ſhake me, that in fine I was glad to yéeld: &amp; moreouer they wil not forget to alleage the infirmity of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the example of <hi>Dauid,</hi> of <hi>S. Peter</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as we are naturallie verie eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and copious, to excuſe our faultes. But if wee muſt come once to peize them &amp; to weigh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> throughlie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne them &amp; humble our ſelues in the preſence of God, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wee are as dumbe as fiſhes, and wée cannot in anie caſe abide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man ſhoulde depaint and liuelie
<pb facs="tcp:21489:41"/> repreſent them vnto vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by this means we maie be brought into the knowledge of them, and ſo to deteſt them. But and if we be reproued for them, we doe either flatly denie them, if anie waie we can, or at leaſt we ſéeke to couer them and to leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen them by all meanes poſſible. And whence commeth that? Surelie from our corruption, and from the loue of our ſelues, which Satan knoweth full well how to vſe, that he maie thereby bleare our vnderſtanding, or els ſtrike vs ſtark blinde, to the ende we maie not ſée the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil fauouredneſſe and filthineſſe of our faultes, and that we maie not perceiue the danger wherein we are, nor ſéek anie waie or meanes to eſcape thence.</p>
            <p>Now ſure I am that there is no one of you that is come ſo farre, as that hee wil go about to denie ſo manifeſt a fault as yours is, that is to holde and auouche that he hath not offended, for ſuch a one ſhould ſhew himſelfe to be too deſperatly hardned, blinded by Satan, &amp; a ſworne enemie to his owne ſaluation. But we maie wel preſume and beléeue that ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie which haue not as yet forſaken the world, neither are gone farre in renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb facs="tcp:21489:41"/> themſelues, wil haue theſe and the like excuſes readie to alleage: which are euen as manie pillowes or cuſhions which Satan, the fleſhe, and the worlde laie vnder your elbowes, that they may lull and rocke faſt aſléepe your poore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, For when al your excuſes ſhal be wel weighed and conſidered, it maie be they ſhal haue ſome colour, and be of ſome importance with men, which are naturallie moued with ſuch affections &amp; humane paſſions which corrupt their iudgement: but when they ſhall be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined according to the worde of God, which peyzeth al thinges aright, then they ſhal come ſhort, and ſhal be of none importance. You wil ſaie then firſt of al that you did not this voluntarilie, and of purpoſed malice. I graunt you that, and yet God woulde not haue anie to come euen ſo farre. But would you haue done it if you had not had a will to doe it? your wil could not be ſo driuen and enforced, but that you might haue auoided ſuch a miſchiefe and inconuenience, if you had had a true zeale of the glorie of God, and an earneſt deſire of your own ſaluation, an holie affection to edifie your poore
<pb facs="tcp:21489:42"/> neighbours, and a right and good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Nowe you are ſo conuict in your ſelues, that theſe things haue bin ſo ſmal &amp; ſle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der in you, that they haue bin weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed downe with the weight of your affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wherto you haue yelded your ſelues yea euen with a ſtraunge kind of reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: for what maner violence was this which you alleage for your excuſe? Haue you reſiſted vnto bloud? Haue you béene bound with chaines and caſt into filthie dungeons? Haue you bin racked by tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or iudged to be burnt quicke? And albeit God had laide all theſe trials vpon you, &amp; that he would haue bin glorified in your patience &amp; conſtancie, what had bin your dutie to haue done then? ought yée to haue falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> back? ought you to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to haue drunk of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cup of the ſon of God? to haue borne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yoke of his order, &amp; to haue bin aſſociated vnto ſuch a goodly &amp; honorable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie of martirs, whoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial doth and ſhal remain for euer, not only honorable, but alſo bleſſed &amp; holy, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of God, &amp; who eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now reign &amp; triumph w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſus Chriſt, being crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with glory, &amp; eternal immortalitie. If I ſaie, god had brought ſuch ſharp tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als
<pb facs="tcp:21489:42"/> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you as he brought vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you might beare witnes of his holie truth, &amp; it had ſo falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you had done then as now you haue done, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auoiding of tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; ſo cruel death: you might by good right haue bin counted reuolts, diſloyal &amp; traitors to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon of God, neither ſhoulde you haue deſerued to beare the name of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. How vile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how ſhameful, &amp; howe da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable is your cowardlines and backſliding, ſeeing you ſhould only haue bin depriued for a time of ſome temporal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities? you haue made more accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a litle pelfe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the glorie of God, of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly treaſures, and of your own ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. You haue bin afraid to looſe your goods, and haue no whit feared to looſe Gods fauor, &amp; to incurre his wrath &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure. You haue quaked &amp; tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled at the friuolous woordes of men which are nought but worms of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, when they threatned you with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fiſcation of goods &amp; haue not tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled at the terrible threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the iudgements of God, neither haue you feared the fire of his wrath and curſe more than your goods and your ſelues. But I praie you what letted you to ſaue, if not all your goodes, yet the
<pb facs="tcp:21489:43"/> moſt part of them, ſéeing you had ſuche leiſure and time to bethinke your ſelues, and to ſet your thinges in order? Surely you cannot ſay that you were taken at vnawares as by ſome ſodaine clappe of lightning: For if you woulde haue ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned your eies you might haue ſéene long before a cloude ariſing, which did threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to Fraunce ſome great tempeſt. You were oftentimes aduertiſed by your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors that the vnthankfulneſſe of men, the contempt of the graces of God, the ſimple reformation which was to be ſéen in manie, the coldneſſe of zeale and loue, too too great libertie which euerie man gaue himſelfe to liue as he liſt, ſhaking off the yoke of Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline, and not regarding anie admonitions whatſoeuer, which were giuen &amp; made in the name of God: you haue I ſaie bin often told that all theſe thinges woulde without al doubt prouoke the Lorde to wrath, and would bring vppon vs ſome great calamities. This was done to the ende euerie man might humble himſelfe and preuent the wrath of God, by true repentance and amendement: this was to the ende euerie man might be readie,
<pb facs="tcp:21489:43"/> and might make prouiſion for patience, ſtrength, conſtancie, faith, hope, and for other ſuche ſpirituall furniture,<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.</note> whereof the Apoſtle ſpeaketh: this was in ſumme to the ende we might prepare our ſelues for the battel, &amp; that we might begge of God thoſe thinges which wee had not of our ſelues. And without all doubt he would haue giuen vs it, if euery man had béene readie and willing to doe his dutie. But what? we haue done quite contrarie (we haue kept our old courſe, &amp; haue become rather woorſe than better: we haue counted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> buſie &amp; importunate felowes which threatned vs with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God: we counted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> too bitter and ſharp which fought our ſaluation by telling vs the trueth we would haue had them to haue preached as we wold haue them, we had itching eares, &amp; we woulde haue had them fedde with ſome vanitie of mans eloquence, for wee loathed the plainneſſe of the word of God. To make ſhort, there were in vs ſo manie wantes, that in ſteade of preuenting the wrath of God, wee did more inflame the ſame: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of preparing &amp; fortifying our ſelues that wée might indure this aſſaulte,
<pb facs="tcp:21489:44"/> we became rechleſſe and careleſſe, and at length ſo white liuered, ſo cowardly and faint hearted, that the more part béeing terrified with the verie ſounde of the trumpe, did yéelde themſelues to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie without making anie reſiſtance. O what a ſhame was this? The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is your backſliding ſo much the more to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſeing you haue deſpiſed the admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wherwith your eares were beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo long before. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which more is, this te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt came not at a ſodain or at vnawares as that of the Maſſacre, but lumbered a long time in the ayre before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clap came. And he whom you had greateſt cauſe to feare (as touching men) ſéemeth to haue bin raiſed vp of God to admoniſh you of that which you were to doe; which was done by edictes and declarations ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade one after another: as if he would haue ſaid, My friendes, ſet your thinges in order, and kéepe your ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that euil which is threatned vnto you. But you haue neglected all that, whether it were becauſe you were drunken with ſome vaine hope which deceiued you, or whether it were becauſe you were reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued rather to ſit vppon your own dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hils,
<pb facs="tcp:21489:44"/> and to abide by your garlicke and onions of Egypt, then to followe Ieſus Chriſt anie more through the deſertes, and anie longer to beare his croſſe. which you loathed at length. Which appeareth by this, in that in ſtéed of preparing your ſelues to newe afflictions, and of follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ieſus Chriſt, euen to the ende, as al thoſe ought to doe which are his true Diſciples, and deſire to attaine to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the high calling: in ſtéed therof, I ſaie you haue promiſed to your ſelues ſome reſt and eaſe of the fleſh: but you were deceiued, as al thoſe ſhal be which ſo caſt their accountes without their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſſe. This was then your ouerthrow.</p>
            <p>Now I doubt not but that manie ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay in trueth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had many lets, and were aſſailed by grieuous te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations, ſeeing they were charged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a family, &amp; deſtitute of means. To be ſhort, it may be, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many other poore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had manie lets &amp; hindera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: &amp; for this cauſe they are rather to bee pitied, yet ſo it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are not excuſable before god for al this: &amp; they muſt al yeld the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues as guiltie: for howſoeuer it be, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it pleaſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord to cal vs, we muſt folow him w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out looking back, &amp; without
<pb facs="tcp:21489:45" rendition="simple:additions"/> looking vpon the hardneſſe of the waie by the which wee muſt goe. The Iſraelites could not ſee with the eies of the fleſhe, howe the Lord did deliuer them out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyrannie and ſlauery of Egypt, how they eſcaped out of that diſtreſſe wherein they ſaw the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, hauing the mountains on the right hande &amp; on the left, &amp; hauing the read ſea before them, and the hoaſt of the Egyptians behinde them: alſo how the Lorde prouided for their neceſſities in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſert, &amp; how he brought them into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed land: they ſaw none of theſe things I ſaie, notwithſtanding they followed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> calling of the Lorde, referring the euents and iſſues of al things to his prouidence: which fel out wel w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And thus ought thoſe to haue done which alleage for their excuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſaid ſtraites: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, they ſhold haue ſhut their eies againſt al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which fleſh &amp; blood coulde ſet before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to turne them awaie, and they ſhould haue giuen vp the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to the prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie father, who feedeth the foules of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aire, &amp; who knoweth wel y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes how to prouide bread for his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his calling, &amp; not onelie the meanes, but hath alſo a will to doe it, as hee hath
<pb facs="tcp:21489:45"/> promiſed. And indeede, euen then, when we ſee nothing, which waye ſoeuer wee turne our eies, but matter of diſpaire, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> principally doth our faith ſhewe it ſelfe, when notwithſtanding al lets &amp; hindera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces we truſt in God, &amp; hope contrarie to hope, after the example of <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al excuſes which theſe men can alleage to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, cannot any way iuſtifie them. But &amp; if the hinderances were ſuch, that they had no way nor means to eſcape out certain it is that this was an euident ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Lord called them to beare witnes of his truth: &amp; therfore ought they rather to haue died the death tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue denied the ſonne of God ſo ſhamefully. To make ſhort, it behooued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either to flie, or els to ſuffer, ſeing the Lord refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it to their choice, and called them to doe either the one or the other.</p>
            <p>Now if theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be without excuſe (as they be indeede) howe muche more thoſe which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſo excuſe themſelues, if they wil ſpeake trueth? And yet were there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhewed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſo ſlack &amp; ſo faint harted, &amp; more redy to come to parle, &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to yeld the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enimy. Thoſe to whom God had giuen more means to
<pb facs="tcp:21489:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> reſiſt and ſtand ſtedfaſt, thoſe that might quicklie haue eſcaped the danger, &amp; euen haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted their poore brethren, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging them, &amp; reaching them out the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to draw them out of the mire &amp; filth: thoſe are they, I ſaie, which haue ſhewed themſelues moſt cowardlie &amp; cold, either becauſe they had more to looſe (I meane more myre &amp; earth, and leſſe godlineſſe &amp; feare of God) or els becauſe it grieued them to forgoe their pleaſures and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, to incurre feare, to indure the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities &amp; diſturba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of baniſhment &amp; ſuch like things. They could wel finde in their hearts to goe into paradiſe by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> large &amp; wide way &amp; gate: but Ieſus chriſt ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this is the waie that leadeth to deſtruction, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the narrow waie &amp; ſtrait gate leade to eternall life. So that theſe men are the more guilty before God, the leſſe excuſe they haue. But furthermore you wil obiect y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am too rigorous, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue no regarde to mans infirmitie, &amp; that there is none ſo good but he doth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend &amp;c. I anſwere, that your fault can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſufficientlie exaggerate, it is ſo monſtrous and ſcandalous: and it is moſt neceſſarie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you be brought to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of
<pb facs="tcp:21489:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> your maladie and miſerie, that you maie be cured. And as for the infirmitie of our fleſh, I know (I praiſe God) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than I can expreſſe, the Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it better than we, and he taketh pitie and compaſſion thereon, but yet for al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wil not take our excuſes, which wée alleage, for paiment: for it ariſeth from a corrupt fountaine, that is, from ſinne, yea it is ſinne in it ſelfe: and principallie hee condemneth it when wee nouriſh it, cheriſh it, and entertaine it in our ſelues, when wee take pleaſure and flatter our ſelues in it, &amp; when we wil make a buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of it to couer and defend our faultes: we ought rather, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we procéed againſt our ſelues to begin here, that is, firſt of al to condemne our infirmitie, as beeing a fruite of our corruption, and afterward our ſluggiſhnes and ſlackneſſe in that we deſpiſe the means which God ſetteth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs to ſtrengthen our ſelues with al in the power of his ſpirite. If during the time of your proſperitie (at which time the Lorde graunted you grace to take ſome reſt, or at leaſt to take ſome breath) you had wel known your infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this knowledge ingendering
<pb facs="tcp:21489:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> in you a diſtruſtfulneſſe of your ſelues, had ſtirred you vp to craue help at Gods handes euen the ſtrength of his ſpirite, you ſhould not haue fallen into this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience.</p>
            <p>If you ſaie that the loue of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, mothers, wiues, and children, their prouocations, their cries &amp; their teares, the deſire of their good and commoditie, and the feare you had to leaue them ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all manner perils and dangers, or to ſuffer and indure anie harme: if you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage, I ſaie, that al theſe thinges were of great force to make you ſtagger and to abate your courage: I graunt that theſe are great trials, namely to thoſe that haue a tender heart, and that a man muſt be furniſhed with ſingular ſtrength from aboue, that he may be able to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come al thoſe things: I ſaie moreouer, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this humane &amp; natural affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; approued of God, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is wel ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: for he that careth not for thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto him, is worſe than an Infidel, ſaith the Apoſtle:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5</note> but I ſaie therwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all that this affection hath not onelie béene diſordered in you,<note place="margin">Deut. 6. Mat. 24.</note> but alſo ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gely diſordered &amp; vnbrideled. For you know
<pb facs="tcp:21489:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> what that meaneth which the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth at our handes, that we loue him with all our heart, ſtrength, thought, and vnderſtanding: that is to ſay, that there be nothing in the world neither without nor within vs, that may be able to turne vs aſide, how little ſoeuer, from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and perfect loue which we owe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our God and father: moreouer that we loue nothing in this world, of all that which we can and ought to loue, no not our ſelues, but onely in him, and for his ſake, or to ſpeake plainely, that there bee nothing which we loue properlie, but him alone. You know alſo what Ieſus Chriſt ſaith, that if we preferre the loue of our fathers, mothers, wiues, children, brethren, ſiſters, and of our owne life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the loue which we owe vnto him, yea if we hate not all theſe thinges for the loue of him, we can not bee his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and we are not worthie of him.</p>
            <p>This was then a marueilous exceſſiue and diſordered affection that carried you away ſo farre, as to make you forget the loue of your God and father, and of your ſauiour and redéemer Ieſus Chriſt. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, I aſke you this queſtion, what
<pb facs="tcp:21489:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> greater good and commoditie, yea what greater honour you could deſire and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure for your wiues and children, then to ſhew them an example of true godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and of the feare of God, of patience and Chriſtian conſtancie? To carry the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with you (if néed had beene) into ſome place of ſafetie, where God might be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon, ſerued and honored? And there to learne in good time to beare the croſſe of Ieſus Chriſt, that they might haue this honor together with you, namely to weare the liuerie and coller of his order, that you might together be partakers of this bleſſing of the ſonne of God.<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 5.</note> Bleſſed are they which ſuffer perſecution for righteouſnes ſake, for theirs is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen: and of that whereof S. Paule ſpeaketh that if wee ſuffer with him we ſhall raigne with him and ſhall be glorified with him: furthermore, how could you better ſaue them from danger, and prouide for their ſafetie and your owne, then to bring them to this ſtronge dungeon of the houſe of God, that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the church, which is without rifts and frée from vndermining, and which is founded vpon a rocke, and garded by the
<pb facs="tcp:21489:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> celeſtial armies, which lye incamped round about,<note place="margin">Mat. 16. Pſal. 34. Pſ. 125.</note> being couered and inuiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on euery ſide with the fauour of the almightie, being garded, fortified, and defended by the inuincible force of the ſpirit of God.</p>
            <p>To be briefe, what better thing could you do for thoſe that are of your bloud, and for your own ſoules, then to further and procure the ſaluation, the life, and the eternall felicitie of you all? But you haue taken a cleane contrarie courſe, for you haue procured their perdition, their diſhonour and eternall confuſion toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with your owne, and haue drawen them and your ſelues into farre greater danger, then if with your owne handes you had deliuered them vp to the moſte cruel &amp; bloudie cutthroates of the world, or els if you had committed them to the mercie of Lyons, Tygers, and Beares, or of other bruit beaſtes which are mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſſe. For firſt of al, of what benefites, fauours &amp; bleſſings of God haue you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued your ſelues together, ſeing you haue cut your ſelues off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; from the communion of ſaints w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out which there is no bleſſednes
<pb facs="tcp:21489:49" rendition="simple:additions"/> felicitie, ſaluation, neither anie life what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer, but all vnhappines, curſednes, death, ruine and deſtruction, What due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie haue you done to edifie them, when you ſhewed them the example of your cowardlines, trecherie, and diſloialtie? What account will they make to come to Chriſtian religion, ſéeing you make ſo ſmall account thereof? What reuerence will thy giue to Ieſus Chriſt and his doctrine, ſeeing you renounce the ſame ſo cowardlie? To be briefe, what conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and ſtabilitie can be expected at their handes, if they become members of the Church of God, ſéeing you haue ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them and made them to ſtumble by your apoſtaſie? In ſumme then, ſo farre of is it that you haue procured their good and commoditie, in doing that which you haue done, that on the contrary you haue purchaſed them the greateſt euill and curſe that could befall them: for you haue drawen them with you to the way of deſtruction, yea you haue euen thruſt them into hell there to abide for euer, if God bee not mercifull to them and you. Furthermore, what honour haue you procured them in teaching them by your
<pb facs="tcp:21489:49" rendition="simple:additions"/> example, and it may bee, by leading and carying them your ſelues into the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelhouſe to commit whoredome with Idols? Had not this béene greater ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to haue continued in the houſe of the Lord, to haue ſit at the table with the ſonne of God, to haue dronke of his cup, and to haue eaten the bread of Aungels with the Saintes, then to be in the infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous houſe of this great whore, to ſitte with her ruffians and baudes, to receiue at her execrable handes the cup of her filthines and vncleannes, which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle calleth the cup of deuils? Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, into what danger haue you brought both them and alſo your ſelues? Thoſe to whom God hath giuen eies to ſée, ſée by the accompliſhment of the ſignes that were foretold by the ſpirit of God, that Antichriſt doth now put in practiſe his laſt indeuours, ſéeing the meaſure of his impieties and abhominations is growen vp to the full: as he doth plainely declare in theſe laſt times, by that outragious violence which he vſeth nowe as if hee were mad, foming out his rage more fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly then euer againſt the Church of Ieſus Chriſt. And therfore they conclude
<pb facs="tcp:21489:50"/> by the word of God, that the Lord will not be long, neither wil he deferre to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play his fearefull iudgements vpon this curſed Babilon. For which cauſe the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God exhorteth vs to come thence, ſaying: Come out of her my people, that you be not partakers of her ſinnes, and that you be not puniſhed with her: for her ſinnes are come vp to heauen, and God hath remembred her iniquities &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Lo here then a trumpet from heauen which ſoundeth and warneth you that the eternall will ſend out his thunder and lightning vpon Babilon: and yet you are ſo vndiſcréet as to runne into her together with your wiues and children, there to ſaue your ſelues. If you ſée an houſe on fire, or ſome lightning fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen fall vpon it, wil you be ſo fooliſh and mad as to run into it there to ſaue your ſelues and your young children, and that which is deare &amp; pretious vnto you? And yet you haue done thus, ſéeking for life in the middeſt of death, for happines amidſt curſednes, and for ſaluation there where there is nothing but ruine and deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And moreouer, you thinke your ſelues verie wiſe and diſcreet in
<pb facs="tcp:21489:50"/> that you haue gotten you ſuch a couert whiles the haile doth fall vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heads of others. But alas, this is a poore and daungerous couerture, which will at laſt fall vpon your heades, vpon your goods, vpon your wiues and children, if you come not thence with more ſpeed.</p>
            <p>You wil ſay, that that is your deſire, &amp; that you are not entred into it with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie purpoſe that you wil continue there alwaies, &amp; that you hope to returne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, all this do I beléeue: but firſt of al I anſwere you, that you muſt not thus dallie with God, &amp; that it hath fallen out euil with many which haue thus dallied, and that by the iuſt iudgement of God, who will not ſuffer thoſe which mocke him to eſcape ſcotfrée, as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do. For you ſhall very hardly find one of an hundred (of thoſe which did ſometimes reuolt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) which hath made his accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to continue ſtill in that filthy puddle, and which hath not fed himſelfe with ſome vaine hope to return to the church again, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil time ſhould be ouer. But yet it came to paſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Satan taking occaſion hereat, hath by litle &amp; litle extinguiſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmal zeale, &amp; choked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> little quantitie of
<pb facs="tcp:21489:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> good ſéed of godlines and of the feare of God which was in them, that he might more and more tread them down in the ſinke, out of the which they could neuer afterward ariſe by any force, or leaſure. I ſaie nothing but that which you your ſelues know ful well, and the experience whereof you haue ſéene in manie. And how commeth this to paſſe, if not by the iuſt vengeance of God, who depriueth thoſe of his graces, which make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnworthie thereof through their vnthankfulnes, and deliuereth thoſe vp into the power of Sathan which abuſe his mercy? The Lord is not bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue to mercie thoſe that are mockers and contemners of his grace, that hee ſhould graunt it them ſo often as it ſhall pleaſe them to accept it, after that it hath bene offered them ſundrie times, and that they ſhall haue reiected and diſpiſed the ſame, yea after that they ſhall haue troade it vnder their féet, and put it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from them with their haggiſh notes delighting more in filth, then in this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable treaſure and this great and precious pearle: for buying whereof the good huſbandmen and true marchantes
<pb facs="tcp:21489:51"/> of the Lord ſell all that they haue: as Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt teacheth vs by thoſe two pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables which are in the Goſpell.<note place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> It is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a iuſt thing with the lord to puniſh ſuch mockers and profane men, and that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers waies: for to ſome hee denyeth the bleſſing of his grace, whereof they made leſſe account then of a meſſe of pottage, howſoeuer they come to ſéeke it with wéeping and howling, as did that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Eſau. They ſhall crye after me, ſaith the Lord by Ieremie, but I wil not heare them. O then ſome there be whom in his iuſt iudgement he ſuffereth to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo hardned in their euil, and to fal into ſuch brutiſh blockiſhnes, that being without féeling, and not ſeing the déepe gulph of that wretchednes into which they are fallen, they knowe not what néede they haue of the grace of God that they may be deliuered thence: whereby it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe that they neuer craue it at Gods handes, but dye like brute beaſts. There be yet ſome others which are ſorer ſtricken with this lightning of Gods iudgment: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, thoſe whom Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath caſt into ſuch deſpaire, that in ſtéede of comming to god to craue mercy at his
<pb facs="tcp:21489:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> handes, they fly from him, they hate him, they blaſpheme him, &amp; they deſpiſe him: they are miſerably vexed and tormented with remorſe of their conſcience, which is as a worme which gnaweth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende and without ceaſing: or rather like the infernall furies which purſue them, which torment them, which hale them, toſſe them too and fro a thouſande waies, not ſuffering them to take anye eaſe or reſt: to make ſhort, the reſt of their miſerable life which they lead as it were in deſpight of God and of nature, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but a very beginning of hel, and an hydious image of that curſed and more then miſerable condition wherein the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned are and ſhalbe for euer. Thus fared it with Iudas, with Iulian the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtata, and with others. I would faine ſet before your eies that which in our time befell a certaine Apoſtata called Spira, where you might ſée that verified which hath bene ſaid, for in him we haue an example of the terrible and fearefull iudgement of God againſt thoſe which do ſo dally and trifle with his maieſtie, renouncing the profeſſion of his Goſpell, for the auoyding of perſecutions: and
<pb facs="tcp:21489:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> which run after the world for a time, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ſhortly after to returne to the right way againe. But for the auoiding of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixitie I ſend you to the hiſtorie which is common, beſeeching you to read it and to meditate vpon it diligently, not that you may do as this miſerable wretch did, but that you may learne what puniſhment your fault deſerueth which is al one w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his: for he had the ſame knowlege which you haue, he at the beginning of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolting did alleadge the ſame excuſes, and made the very ſame proteſtations, that in time he would returne: But to the ende the Lord might auenge himſelfe of ſo great backſliding, he would not giue him grace ſo to do: for after that Sathan had once taken poſſeſſion of him, hee ſet before his eies the greatnes and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſnes of his ſinne, together with ſuch an hidious and fearefull repreſentation of the iudgment of god, that he deſpaired, and ended his life ſo miſerably, and with ſuch an euident teſtimonie of the iuſt furye and indignation of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt Apoſtacye, that it is a thinge vnpoſſible to ſee ſuch a ſpectakle without great terrour and feare. Now
<pb facs="tcp:21489:53"/> the Lord doth not ſhew like iudgments in this world againſt al reuolts: that is true, yet ſo it is that the iuſt puniſhment which he executeth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome one in this world, ſheweth how deteſtable a thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> renouncing of the goſpel is to him. And if he deferre his iuſt vengeance and doth not execute the ſame vpon ſome certain, yet they ſhal not eſcape ſcotfrée, and their puniſhment ſhall bee no whit the lighter therefore: but on the contrarie their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation ſhall bee ſo much the more gréeuous becauſe they haue abuſed the patience of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note>Now true it is, my brethren, that I count you not amongſt theſe, as I haue alreadie proteſted: but ſo it is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you are entred into the ſelf ſame way which theſe are entred, and are in like danger, if God do not graunt you grace to retire thence by ready &amp; true repentance. It remaineth then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you awake &amp; that throughly at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſounde of this trumpet which the Lorde cauſeth to ſound in your eares, who graunteth vnto you ſuch grace as to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe and exhor you to turne to him. He graunteth you ſometime to bethinke your ſelues &amp; doth now ſet before you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21489:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> meanes of reconciliation becauſe he will not looſe you: take héed you deſpiſe them not:<note place="margin">Pſ. 95.</note> and ſeing you heare his voice this day harde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not your hearts: he calleth you with armes diſplaied, and offereth you his grace, beware you deſpiſe it not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfully, for feare leaſt it be afterward denied you, for a iuſt puniſhment of your vnthankfulnes: the meanes to attaine to this grace is, that you haue true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and true faith: repentance to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you, and to throw you downe euen to hell by a liuely féeling and knowledge of your offence, and by a true apprehending of the iuſt iudgment of God: faith to lifte you vp &amp; to ſet you on foot again in hope, by a right apprehenſion and acceptation of the clemencie and mercy of God. This is then the courſe which you muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue: firſt of al examine &amp; poys the fault which you haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, together with all the circumſtances thereof, not flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring your ſelues any maner of way, and you ſhall be conſtrained to confeſſe that it is as yet greater and more monſtrous. more foule and vile before God then I am able to expreſſe and ſet forth: knowe and acknowledge therein your back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding,
<pb facs="tcp:21489:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> cowardlines, trecherie, diſloyalty and vnthankfulnes moſt deteſtable: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what diſhonor, what iniurie, what outrage you haue done to God your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to Ieſus Chriſte your Sauiour, to your ſelues, your wiues, your children, and to all the whole Church. Thoſe which ſaid they were Gods deare chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, haue forſaken and denyed him: his couenant is broken: Ieſus Chriſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, euen by thoſe whom he had redéemed with the price of his bloud, and by thoſe which had ſworne faith and allegiance to him: the doctrine of his Goſpel is caſt of and conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned as falſe, and the impieties and abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Antichriſt are receiued and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued as true and holy and that by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable confeſſion and abiuration: the Lord is diſhonored and blaſphemed, his holy name is polluted and profaned by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrilegious mouth of profane perſons &amp; infidels: religion is contenmed and there is none account made of it: the kingdome of Ieſus Chriſt is hindered &amp; kept back: your poore neighbours are offended the ſimple ſort is diſcouraged, by your euill example they are falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and run headlong
<pb facs="tcp:21489:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> into the ſame deſtruction whereinto you are fallen: your poore Paſtours are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded and aſhamed, and conſequently diſcouraged by you from returning to till the Lordes field: lo the poore church is forſaken of thoſe which ſaide they were her children, and a cruel and murdering harlot is receiued and acknowledged for the true mother. Lo your true mother is forſaken, grieued, abaſhed, and aſhamed to ſee the ſhamefull backſlyding of her children: ſhe wéepes and wailes by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their deſtruction: the Temple of God it is polluted, the holy Ghoſt is made ſad therewith, and the holy Angels mourne and lament for it: briefely lo here a moſt deteſtable and abhominable Apoſtacie, which comprehendeth ſo great a number of ſo grieuous and horrible crimes, as that the only rehearſall thereof is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to make the hayres of a Chriſtian mans head, that feareth God, to ſtande vpright. Thus then muſt you poys your fault, that it maye ſeeme to you ſo blacke, ſo foule, and ſo ougly, as that it may make you aſhamed in the preſence of God and of his Church.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21489:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Conſider on the other ſide huw much wood and matter you haue miniſtred to ſet on fire the wrath of God againſt you.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 5.</note> You know that the ſcripture ſaith of the wrath and indignation of the Lord, that it is a conſuming fire which ſpoileth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth and deuoureth all that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it méeteth: You know that he is an enimie to ſinne, and that his iuſtice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth that all that be puniſhed which is contrarie to his law, Marke how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny crimes and monſtrous ſinnes are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed in your offence: is not the ſmalleſt of them ſufficient to prouoke him to wrath? Know you not that one onely ſin hath ſometimes ſo prouoked the Lord to wrath, that to puniſh the ſame hee hath cauſed the earth to open and to ſwallow vp thoſe alſo that haue committed it? that he hath made fire come down from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume thoſe which were gilty therof,<note place="margin">Num. 16. Num. 21.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath ſent ſerpents in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes the plague, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſword, &amp; the deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, &amp; other ſcourges to puniſh the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings,<note place="margin">Num. 14.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnthankfulnes, &amp; other ſins of his people? The holy hiſtorie decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth what iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; vengeance y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord hath ſundry times &amp; vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuers occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:21489:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> vſed againſt the Iſraelites. Sometimes they were viſited by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plague, ſomtimes by famine, ſometimes by warre. The lord hath raiſed vp diuers enemies to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute his iudgements vpon them.</p>
            <p>They haue oftentimes had vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> armie of the Philiſtines, oftentimes the Moabits, oftentimes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ammonites &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enemies. Shortlie after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Syrians, the Babylonians, <hi>Antiochus,</hi> &amp; finallie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romaines. They were oftentimes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome &amp; diſcomforted, brought vnder ſubiection &amp; led into captiuitie, &amp; in fine, quite diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fited &amp; deſtroied by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romane empire. To be ſhort, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde did diſplaie the ſeueritie of his iudgementes vppon this people in ſuch ſort, that there is not at this daie anie nation vnder the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oape of heauen more miſerable: which hath continued euer ſithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that fearful iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God which was executed vppon this people in the ſacking and deſtruction of Ieruſalem: ſo that the verie markes of the wrath of God do continue ſo déep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie engrauen in all this miſerable race, that thoſe which perceiue them not, haue none eies to ſee withall. And wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore came all this vppon them? Euen
<pb facs="tcp:21489:56" rendition="simple:additions"/> becauſe they had treacherouſly broken y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couenant of the Lord, becauſe they had forſaken his pure worſhip to run after the idols &amp; ſuperſtitions of the Gentiles, becauſe they had vnthankefully deſpiſed his graces &amp; ſingular fauor which he had graunted them of his own liberalitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had reiected y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaluation which was ſent vnto them: and finallie becauſe they had put to death the Lord of glory, who came to ſaue them. You wil ſaie that you are not culpable of ſuch crimes: and this is our vndoing, when in ſteede of profiting by the examples of the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of God which are propoſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in the ſcriptures, we poſte them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vnto others. But the ſpirite of God iudgeth otherwiſe touching them,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> when he ſaith by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that theſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes which came vpon the people of the Iewes, were examples for vs: and that theſe thinges are written to put vs in minde, vpon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ends of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde are come. But what is the moſt mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous crime that euer the Iewes did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and for the which they are ſet before the eies of the whole worlde for a ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the iuſt wrath and anger of God?
<pb facs="tcp:21489:56"/> euen becauſe they had crucified the Lord of glorie. And now the ſpirite of GOD ſpeaking by the Apoſtle to the Hebrues calleth this which you haue done,<note place="margin">Heb. 6</note> and do as yet contrarie to your owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the crucifying of the Sonne of God afreſhe, and the ſetting of him to bee reproched. Then I praie you what puniſhment doth your fault deſerue? call to mind the threatninges which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Scripture againſt ſuche backſlidinges and trecheries, againſt ſuch vnthankfulneſſe, againſt ſuch pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and profanings of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of God, againſt ſuch deſpiſing of his graces, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuche Apoſtaſies, abiurations and renouncinges of the ſonne of God, and of the doctrine of his Goſpell: to bee ſhort, againſt ſuch offences as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of yours is. You know that the Lord calleth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a ielous God, to ſhew that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide ſuche iniurie to be done to his maieſtie. Wherefore he doth alſo threate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hee wil viſite the iniquitie of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vppon the children vntill the third and fourth generation of thoſe that hate him.<note place="margin">Ex. 20.</note> Now I haue alreadie ſhewed you that after you had forſaken his ſide, that
<pb facs="tcp:21489:57"/> you might aſſociate your ſelues with his enemies, hée cannot take you for anie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but for haters of him, ſo long as you continue with them. And furthermore, this is to hate the Lord, when a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to impieties and idolatries whereby he is diſhonoured.</p>
            <p>Wherefore this threatning appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to you, as doth that alſo which he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth againſt thoſe that take his name in vaine, ſaying, that hee will not holde them guiltleſſe.<note place="margin">Exo. 20.</note> And haue not you taken his name in vaine when you became vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull and periured perſons breaking &amp; violating the faith and promiſe which you had made to him? Doe not you as yet take his name in vaine, when you, through your reuolting are the cauſe that it is polluted, diſhonoured and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the wicked once? Moreouer, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider I praie you a litle what the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning importeth which the ſonne of God vſeth againſt thoſe which ſhall forſake him, &amp; ioyne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with his enimies: which ſhal be aſhamed of him and of his Goſpel: which ſhal renounce him before men, which ſhal ſéek to ſaue their life, by renouncing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth.<note place="margin">Mat. 12.</note> 
               <hi>He that is not with
<pb facs="tcp:21489:57" rendition="simple:additions"/> me,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is againſt me, and hee that gathereth not with mee ſcattereth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad.</hi> And what is it to be againſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt and to ſcatter abroade, but to be counted his enemies. And what inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment can you looke for at his handes at that laſt daie, and howe miſerable ſhal your eſtate bee, if hee account you ſuch? Furthermore what meaneth that threatening which hée pronounceth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe which ſhall bee aſhamed of him &amp; of his wordes, ſaying that he will alſo bee aſhamed of them: when hee ſhall come in the glorie of his Father with the holy Angels? Surelie the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof is, that hee wil not account them his, but will reiect thoſe which ſhall ſhew themſelues ſo vnthankfull as to be aſhamed of the ſon of God,<note place="margin">Mar. 8.</note> who was not aſhamed of our poore and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable nature, but hath done vs ſo greate honor as to ioyne &amp; couple himſelfe with vs, honoring vs with this title of brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hee might vnite and knit vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God his father. Moreouer, conſider what that denying and renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing which he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to thoſe ſhall haue denied and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced him before men, doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
<pb facs="tcp:21489:58"/> when he ſaith, that he wil denie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before God his father, and holie Angels: which is confirmed by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> that <hi>If wee denie him hee will denie vs alſo.</hi> You are not ignoraunt that this is euen the extreameſt woe and curſe, to bee denied and reiected of the ſonne of God. Marke alſo what a curſe hee pronounceth againſt thoſe that giue offence, when hée ſaith: <hi>Woe bee to him by whom offences come:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 17. Mat. 18.</note> 
               <hi>it were better for him that hee were caſt into the ſea, and that hee had a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone hanged about his neck.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede, what puniſhment thinke you bee deſerueth who by his euill example ſhal bee the cauſe of the deſtruction of his poore brother, for whom the ſonne of God did ſhedde his precious bloud?<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> Set before you the threatninges which are denounced againſt thoſe that pollute the temple of God,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. Eph. 4.</note> which make ſad the ſpirite of God, the holie Angels, and all the whole Churche. Remember that which you once learned,<note place="margin">Luke 12.</note> that <hi>the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant which knoweth his maiſters will and doth it not ſhalbe puniſhed dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: and that it ſhalbe eaſier for thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:21489:58" rendition="simple:additions"/> of Sodom and Gomorrha at the laſt daie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12.</note> 
               <hi>then for thoſe that haue deſpiſed the day of their viſitation.</hi> To be brief, iudge you what paine and puniſhment he deſerueth, who putteth in place of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> execrable idol of Antichriſt, abiuring the trueth of the one, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing the falſhood of the other. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, feare leaſt you be inwrapped in that fearefull iudgement which the ſonne of God denou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth againſt that curſed Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.</note> into whoſe boſom you haue thrown your ſelues: and returne into <hi>Noahs</hi> arke again, if you will eſcape the floud of the wrath of God, which threatneth the whole earth.<note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> 
               <hi>It is a fearful thing</hi> ſaieth the Apoſtle, <hi>to fal into the hands of the liuing God.</hi> The temporal iudgements which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord did execute vpon Sodome and Gomorrha vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Iewes &amp; others, and which he executeth dailie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, are in very deed terrible &amp; fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and make mens haire ſtand vpright when they heare of them. But this is nothing in compariſon of the fearefull iudgement which muſt bee executed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked after this life:<note place="margin">Eſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. 2. Cor. 2.</note> for as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eie hath not ſeene, the eare hath not hearde,
<pb facs="tcp:21489:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> and mans heart hath not conceiued, nor compriſed the good things which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord hath prepared for theſe which loue &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him: ſo likewiſe on the contrary we may ſaie &amp; that truelie, that the paines, the anguiſhes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eternal torments which are prepared for the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned in hel cannot be comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by mans vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding. For if we could comprehend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie thinking therupon ſhould cauſe in vs an intollerable aſtoniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; feare. The holy ſcripture doth ſometimes repreſent them vnto vs by vtter darknes, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by eternal bands, by wéeping &amp; gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of téeth,<note place="margin">Mat. 12. 1. Pet. 3. Apoc. 20. Mat. 13. Eſ. 66. Mat. 9. mat. 19. mar. 9.</note> by the worme that gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth without ceaſſing, &amp; which neuer dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and by fire that neuer is quenched: not that there is any proportion betwéen the eternall tormentes, and the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme dolours and diſtreſſes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man can imagine in all theſe thinges: but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end it may apply it ſelfe to our dulnes, and giue vs ſome vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of thoſe infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and vnſpeakeable paynes, which the damned ſhal ſuffer, it deſcribeth them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs by ſimilitudes taken from thinges which are terrible and fearful. Now this is not to the ende we maie be put in anie
<pb facs="tcp:21489:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> vaine feare, as litle children are made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid with ſcarrebugs, but that we maie be throughlie afraid indéede of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God: that we maie walke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in feare: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we maie hate ſinne which inflameth Gods wrath againſt men: and that it may make vs ſéek peace and reconciliation with God when wee haue offended him. This is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende for which (my brethren) I put you in mind of theſe things, foraſmuch as I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion and ſaluation. What muſt you do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? you muſt ſet before your eies the greatnes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foulenes, the filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and deformitie of your fault, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you maie be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded and aſhamed in your ſelues that you haue ſhewed your ſelues ſo cowardlie and ſo vnthankful towarde ſo good a father: that you maie be beaten downe with terrour and trembling, and with feare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgement of God which you haue deſerued:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> that you maie iudge and condemne your ſelues, that you bee not iudged and condemned of the Lorde: to make ſhort, that you maie come like poore offenders with ropes about your necks, to craue pardon at Gods handes, caſting downe your ſelues at his féete by
<pb facs="tcp:21489:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> true humilitie, yea euen plunging your ſelues (as men ſay) in the déep dungeons of hell.</p>
            <p>Marke héere where your conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt beginne, to witte, at true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, if you deſire to bee receyued into fauour: for an ancient father ſaith, Hell is the waie to come to heauen: that is to ſaie, that ſuch caſting downe and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of poore ſinners, confeſſing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting their faultes, accuſing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning themſelues, and which think themſelues worthie to bée drowned in the déepe pitte of Hell, is the true pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration and diſpoſition to receiue the grace of GOD. For hée which hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth him ſelfe ſhall bee exalted. The Lorde is nigh to heartes that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate,<note place="margin">Mat. 23. Luke 14.4. Pet. 5. Pſal. 34.</note> contrite and humble. Hee ſaueth thoſe that are broken in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Afterwarde, being prepared by ſuche a compunction and contrition of heart proceeding from a right knowledge and diſpleaſure conceyued of, and for your ſinne, and therewithall from a true knowledge of the iuſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God, you muſt come out of this depth by the
<pb facs="tcp:21489:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> meanes of faith: which ſhall comforte your broken heartes: and will aſſure your fearefull conſciences, and wil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort your deſolate ſoules: it will teache you that <hi>the Lord wils not the death of a ſinner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ez. 18.</note> 
               <hi>but rather that he bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted and liue:</hi> alſo that hee hath promiſed to poore and miſerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners which ſhall turne from their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked wayes, that hee will caſt all their ſinnes into the bottome of the Sea, ſo that they ſhall neuer bee anie more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred. <hi>Turne you, turne you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mich. 7 Ez.. 18.33.</note> 
               <hi>from your wicked waies: why will you die you houſe of Iſraell?</hi> ſayth the Lorde. Returne then, and repent of al your tranſgreſſions, and your iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhall not be imputed and laid to your charge. <q>Turne you vnto mee with all,<note place="margin">Io. 2.</note> your whole hearte with faſting, wée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and mourning. Rent your hearts, and not your garmentes &amp; turne to the Lorde your God, for he is gentle &amp; merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſlowe to wrath and of greate pitie, and ſuche a one as is ſorie for your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions.<note place="margin">Eſ. 1.</note> Though your ſinnes were, as redde as ſcarlet, yet ſhall they be as white as ſnowe: and though they
<pb facs="tcp:21489:61" rendition="simple:additions"/> were as purple, yet ſhal they be made as white as wooll.</q> But who is hee that ſhall make them white? Faith ſhall teache you that it is the bloud of the ſonne of GOD which cleanſeth you from all ſinne: that it is he who died for our ſinnes, and roſe againe for our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. The fault which you haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted is great and monſtrous, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth great and grieuous condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as you haue alreadie hearde, and as the trueth is: but yet not ſo greate but that you maie haue forgiueneſſe of the ſame, vnleſſe you through your ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacie and want of repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce do make it irremiſſible.</p>
            <p>The Lorde is iuſt, yea and a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere puniſher of the offences of all thoſe which doe obſtinatelie perſeuere there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103. Ezech. 18.33.</note> and which will not giue place to his admonitions: but yet hee is alſo full of compaſſion and pitie towarde poore ſinners which acknowledge their faultes, which humble themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> which with weeping teares, ſighes and feruent praiers aſke pardon at his handes. If wee confeſſe our ſinnes ſaieth Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:21489:61" rendition="simple:additions"/> is faithfull to forgiue vs them. Hee which confeſſeth and acknowledgeth his treſpaſſes, and forſaketh them,<note place="margin">Prou. 28.</note> ſhall obtaine mercie, ſaieth <hi>Salomon.</hi> I graunt your ſinne is great: but yet Gods mercie is greater.<note place="margin">Rom. 5. Heb. 4.</note> Where ſinne hath abounded, ſaieth the Apoſtle, there grace hath abounded much more. Let vs drawe néere then with aſſurance to the throane of grace, that wee maie obtaine mercie, and finde grace to bee holpen in due time. This is the exhortation which the ſpirite of God maketh vnto you, ſpeaking by the Apoſtle to the Hebrues, that hee maie take from you all diſtruſt of reconciliation and of grace. There bee examples in the Scriptures which will well fitte your purpoſe for this matter: as that of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes,</hi> and that of <hi>Peter.</hi> Which I praie you reade and meditate vppon them diligentlie, not to the ende you maie flatter and bring your ſelues faſt on ſleepe in the infirmitie of your fleſhe, and that you maie thereby couer, excuſe, and leſſen your ſinne, as manie doe to their iudgement and condemnation: for ſuch exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples are not ſet before vs to this
<pb facs="tcp:21489:62" rendition="simple:additions"/> ende, but rather to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end you may ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and arme your ſelues againſt the temptations of Satan, who, if he ſée that God toucheth your hearts with anie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, wil do what he can to caſt you headlong into diſpaire: moreouer, it is to the end you maie come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> throne of the grace of God by the ſelf ſame waie, &amp; may enter in by the verie ſame gate wherby they came &amp; entred in thither. And what waie &amp; gate is this? it is true repentance, and a true &amp; liuelie faith, accompanied with true amendement without which all the reſt is as nothing.</p>
            <p>Marke what <hi>Dauid</hi> did. So ſoone as he was tolde of his fault by the Prophet <hi>Nathan,</hi> hee ſought no ſtarting holes or friuolous excuſes to cloake or couer the ſame anie manner of waie, but on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrarie hee confeſſeth it, and doeth fréelie acknowledge it: he himſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth it, and accuſeth himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God: he doth wonderfullie humble himſelfe with wéeping, ſobbing, ſighing, night and daie. And as he was not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to committe the ſinne, no more was he aſhamed to confeſſe and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the ſame openlie, and as it
<pb facs="tcp:21489:62" rendition="simple:additions"/> were to make an honourable amendes for the ſame before the whole Churche that was in his time, and that was to come afterwarde. For the Pſalmes which hee made are as it were a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like confeſſion: to be briefe, hee ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all tokens and teſtimonies of a true penitent heart, which was contrite and humbled through the feeling of ſinne, and by the knowledge of the wrath of GOD, which beateth him downe euen to the depth, afterwarde hee riſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine by the meanes of faith, which ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth before him the greatneſſe and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the compaſſions and mercies of this moſt mercifull father: to whom he maketh recourſe with feruent praier to craue pardon and mercie. Which thing hee doth with certaine perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and aſſuraunce that the Lord would receyue him to mercie, as hee did through his grace. Marke then what manner repentaunce and faith that of <hi>Dauids</hi> was, and what was the fruite thereof. Nowe all this was acompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a readie amendement: for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the Prophete was humbled before the Lorde, after that hee had
<pb facs="tcp:21489:63" rendition="simple:additions"/> craued pardon, and after that hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that the wrath of GOD con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued againſt him was appeaſed, and that his conſcience was at reſt, what doeth hee? Doeth hee lye wallowing ſtill in his filthe? Doeth hee driue off to amende him ſelfe, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire his fault vntill ſuche time as hee might commodiouſlie doe it without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie lette or hinderaunce of other buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Not ſo, but hee reſolueth out of hande to walke all the reſt of his life in the feare and obedience of the Lorde, conſecrating him ſelfe whollie to his ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Thus did <hi>Manaſſes</hi> king of <hi>Iuda:</hi> for after that hee was tolde of his faultes and iniquities, not by ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, but euen by the Lord himſelfe, who becauſe he would not looſe him,<note place="margin">1. Chr. 33.</note> ſpake to him with his fatherlie rodde, deliuering him vp into the handes of the Aſſyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, which bounde him with mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and chaines, and carried him to Babylon.</p>
            <p>After that hee was thus viſited by the Lorde, it is ſaid that he humbled himſelf before him, that is to ſaie, that hee
<pb facs="tcp:21489:63" rendition="simple:additions"/> acknowledged and confeſſed his faultes with griefe and ſorrow, when he percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the wrath of God which he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. It is ſaid further, that hee prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto the Lord, that is, he had recourſe vnto his grace and mercie, with full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and aſſurance that he ſhould ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it. As indéed the Lord was merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto him: for it is ſaid that hee heard his prayer, he receiued him into fauour againe, and made him returne to Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem that he might eſtabliſh him again in his kingdome. Hereupon inſued a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die chaunge and amendment: for he tooke away the ſtrange gods and idols that were in the houſe of the Lord: he broke downe all the altars which he had built contrarie to his commandement: hee ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dified the true altar of the lord, and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereon peace offerings, and ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of praiſe. Alſo he gaue commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t throughout al Iuda that they ſhould ſerue the Lord the God of Iſrael: to bee ſhort he made ſuch and ſo readie an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of all his faultes, that he did indéede declare that there was no feig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning nor hipocriſie in his repentance and in his faith, but that it was pure, intire,
<pb facs="tcp:21489:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſincere. Such was his reuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſuch was that of Sainct Peter. True it is indéede, that there is not ſo ample men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of it in the Goſpell, as of that of Dauid, and that of Manaſſes: for it is onely ſaid that after that Sainct Peter had denyed his maiſter, and that Ieſus Chriſt had beheld him, the Cocke cruel then was he ſo well awaked and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the quicke,<note place="margin">Mat. 26. Mat. 14. Luk. 22.</note> that he ruſhed out of the Prieſtes houſe, and wept bitterly. Now that which followed thereupon, ſheweth plainely that his fault was forgiuen. For Ieſus Chriſt tooke him afterward for his diſciple, and continued him in his office of an Apoſtle. Then wee maye conclude that this faith and repentance was true and intire: for that his bitter wéeping ſhewed that he was throughly touched with his fault, and that he was extreemely grieued at it, not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſaw the puniſhment which hée had deſerued if God would haue hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him ſharpely and ſeuerely, but prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally by reaſon of his too monſtrous vnthankfulnes, backſliding, and diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie which made him aſhamed before God and men. If then his repentance
<pb facs="tcp:21489:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> were true and intire, whereby hee was beaten downe euen to hell, we may well ſay that his faith was of the ſelfe ſame ſtampe, and that this looke which the Lord gaue him was of marueilous force and efficacie: ſéeing that being fallen ſo farre, and hauing committed ſuch an horrible ſinne, that (as they ſay) he was not ſufficient inough to puniſh it: yet was he not ſwallowed vp with diſpaire, but he was raiſed vp out of that dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of deſtruction, euen by apprehending a greater depth then that was: that is the infinite depth of the riches of the grace and mercie of God, whereunto he had recourſe, with full aſſurance that this moſt bountifull and mercifull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther woulde take pittye and compaſſion on him. You ſee then the repentaunce and the excellent faith of this holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle: and alſo how hee ſealeth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth all by a ſodaine and true amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for immediately after that he ſaw the breaknecke of deſtruction, and the wofull and miſerable eſtate whereinto he was fallen, hee came thence without delay, and then went to ſeeke his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren
<pb facs="tcp:21489:65" rendition="simple:additions"/> and companions, that is, he came within the liſts of the Church again how ſmall ſoeuer it were at that time, and in how poore and miſerable eſtate ſoeuer it was according to the world, ſo that the poore faithfull could looke for nothing but for the croſſe, tribulations, and perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, conſidering the ſharpe intertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which the ſoueraigne maiſter and head of the Church had and found.</p>
            <p>This then was the way and gate wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>Dauid, Manaſſes,</hi> and S. <hi>Peter</hi> had acceſſe vnto the throne of that grace and mercie of God. The verye ſelfe ſame thing is taught vs by the hiſtorie of the prodigall ſonne, which Ieſus Chriſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe in the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Luk. 15.</note> to ſhew vs on the one ſide how greatly they are blindes and voide of vnderſtanding, which vpon any occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whatſoeuer forſake the houſe of their heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father, without y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which there is nothing but méere hunger, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, miſerie, wo and curſednes. On the other ſide this ſerueth to teach vs by what meanes we may come and bee receiued into fauour. This was then a fooliſh ſonne, yea blinde and bewitched of Satan: who finding (it maye bee) his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb facs="tcp:21489:65" rendition="simple:additions"/> gouernment and diſcipline too hard and auſtere, and being deſirous to follow his fooliſh affections and diſordered de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, doth withdraw himſelfe from his ſaid father, goeth out of his houſe, and runneth after his owne luſtes: he falleth ſhortly after into a moſt pitious and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable eſtate: he which refuſed to ſit at his fathers table, doth now ſit at table with hogges: he which diſdained good and honorable intertainement, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite and delicate meates &amp; iunkates whereof he had ſufficient, cannot now fill himſelfe with the meat of hogges: hee which deſpiſed the goodly and pretious ornaments wherewith he was cloathed when he was in his fathers houſe, goeth now all tattered and torne like a begger: to make ſhort, he which might haue bene in full good caſe, if he had would, is nowe accurſed and brought to vtter deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on through his own folly, and conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnworthie euer to come within his fathers dores, and to haue ſo much as a good looke of him whom hee had ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly offended. Lo here then a childe that was vtterly loſt, depriued of al good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, honor and felicitie, and plunged as
<pb facs="tcp:21489:66" rendition="simple:additions"/> it were in a gulph of woe, ſhame, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch. What remaineth then for him but to diſpaire? And yet hee taketh not that courſe, but the quite contrarie: for he commeth to himſelfe, hee perceiueth his wretchednes, he bewaileth his eſtate, hee is diſpleaſed with himſelfe for his ſinne, hee reſolueth with him ſelfe to come and humble himſelfe before his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whom he had offended, hee purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to craue pardon of him, aſſuring himſelfe of his goodnes and mercie, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallie he commeth out of that filth, and without anie more a doe to his father he comes, he confeſſeth and acknowledgeth his ſinne to him, ſaying that he had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt heauen and againſt him, and he counteth himſelfe vnworthy to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for his ſonne, and hauing none other meanes left but to flye to his mercie, he beſeecheth him to take pitie and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vpon him, and to graunt him this grace that hee woulde receiue him into his houſe, if not as his childe, yet at leaſt as one of his hyred ſeruauntes: acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging with Dauid that the condition of the poore porters of Gods houſe is farre more bleſſed and honourable then<note place="margin">Pſ. 84.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:21489:66"/> that of the greateſt monarches of the earth which are without the Church.</p>
            <p>Thus did this poore prodigall chylde, that he might eſcape out of that wofull miſerie into which he was fallen, and that hee might recouer that good, that honour, and that felicitye which hee had loſt: as indeede all fell out ſo well, that hee findeth his father better diſpoſed, more ready, and better inclyned to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue him (not as a ſeruant, but as a ſon) then he durſt deſire. In like manner you ſee that the true and only meanes to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne grace and mercye at the Lordes handes, is true repentaunce, a true faith, and true amendment.</p>
            <p>Lo then, my brethren, what courſe you muſt obſerue: lo here the way which you muſt follow: lo here the gate wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you muſt enter in vnto the Lorde to obtayne his fauour. But marke well the band and coniunction of theſe thynges which cannot be anſwered: for deceiue not your ſelues, vnleſſe you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend your fault you may wel ſaye that you acknowledge it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you are grieued at it, that you condemn it, &amp; that you count
<pb facs="tcp:21489:67"/> it ſo grieuous and ſo monſtrous, as that it deſerueth a thouſand deathes and a thouſand hels, if there were ſo many, yet all this is nothing but meere hypocriſie and mocking of God and men. In like manner if you ſay that you haue a true and certaine aſſurance in the goodnes &amp; mercy of God,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> that he will take pitie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, and will giue you grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to his Church: that alſo ſhalbe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a falſe and peruerſe perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and rather a carnall aſſurance and confidence then a true faith: to bee ſhort, all that ſhal be nothing but a méere moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kery of God, and an abuſing of his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and conſequently a meanes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame his anger ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more againſt you, if there withal you ſhew not in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that you do truely repent, and that your faith is frée from al diſſimulation, and hipocriſie. This effect is nothing els but a readie change &amp; amendment wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto you are exhorted in the name of God. For execution wherof we need not here ſtand vpon particulars, you knowe my meaning wel inough. There remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth nothing for you to do but to haue a good and fréewil, proceeding from a true
<pb facs="tcp:21489:67" rendition="simple:additions"/> zeale of God, and from a feruent deſire of your ſaluation, coupled with an holy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to aduaunce the kingdome of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and to edifie his church.</p>
            <p>If the very ſame occaſions which made you fall, do nowe preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues before your eies and keepe you from amending and redreſſing your of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, whether it be in regard of your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, of your goods, of your commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or whether it be in regard of your own perſons and of your kinſmen, or be it in regard of your other circumſtances: be you ful wel aſſured that is Sathans doing, whoſe drift it is to plunge you dée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in the dunge and filth, and more and more to inwrap and intangle you in his nets, that you may not eſcape him. But giue no place to the ſubtilties and falſe perſwaſions of this enimie: reſiſt him and hee will flye from you, ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. He will ſet before you a thouſand difficulties and impoſſibilities therby to aſtoniſh you, and to keepe you backe, if poſſiblie he can, that you maye not be reſolued to enter into the waye of true conuerſion: and if you enter the ſame he will lay a thouſand diſturban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:21489:68"/> and ſtumbling blockes in your waye to ſtop and ſtay you, and to make you retire: he will ſet before your eies the might, the meanes, and the multitude of your enimies, and the ſmall meanes you haue, ſo that you cannot in long time eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape out of this babiloniſh captiuitie: hée will ſet before you the croſſe, the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the ſufferings, the perſecutions, the pouertie, the contempt, the perils and daungers, whereunto thoſe which follow Ieſus Chriſt are dayly ſubiect. On the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide he will promiſe you all reſt, all aſſurance, all good thinges, the honors, pleaſures, delightes and commodities of this life, if you will worſhip him and continue in his ſeruice. But you muſt make him the very ſame anſwere, and giue him the repulſe after the ſelfe ſame ſort as Ieſus Chriſt did, that is by the word of God:<note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> come behinde me Sathan, for it is written &amp;c. You muſt then here take the Spirituall armoure of a Chriſtian knight which the Spirite of God ſetteth downe vnto you by Sainct Paule,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.</note> that is amongſt the reſt, feruent and continuall prayers to the Lorde, the buckler of faith, and the ſword of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb facs="tcp:21489:68" rendition="simple:additions"/> which is the word of God, to beate backe the firie darts of this wicked one: you muſt oppoſe againſt all that which hee ſhall purpoſe vnto you through the inticements of the fleſh and the worlde, that which you ſometimes learned in the Schoole of Chriſt. If then he laye ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blockes croſſe your way to kéepe you from returning to God, beware you ſtumble not at them, but ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſelues in the power of the Spirit of God, and leape ouer them, remembring that graue ſentence of Ieſus Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto but a fewe haue regarde: Bleſſed is he, ſaith he, that is not offended at me: that is, which ſhall not be letted or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, by any occaſion whatſoeuer, to come vnto me, You know full wel what we muſt conclude on the contrarie, that is, that he is vnhappye and more then vnhappy the which ſhall bee offended through him: for in very deede it were better for vs neuer to haue bene borne in this world, then to be ſeparated from Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>As for that which Sathan can ſet before you touching the might, meanes, and multitude of your enimies thereby
<pb facs="tcp:21489:69"/> to make you aſtoniſhed, and touching the féeblenes and infirmitie of the poore Church, and the ſmall meanes it hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the world to helpe it ſelfe, that hereby he may diſcourage you: remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that which is ſpoken ſo often in the Scripture,<note place="margin">2. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that the Lorde hée is a God of power and of hoſtes: remember that which <hi>Eliſeus</hi> ſaith to his ſeruaunt: Thoſe that are with vs are mo then thoſe that are with them.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> Strengthen your ſelues with that which Saincte Paule ſaith: <hi>If God bee with vs who can be againſt vs.</hi> His meaning is not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if god be on our ſide there ſhal not any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger be any enimies to make war againſt vs, but his meaning is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if we haue God on our ſide, we may deſpiſe al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrength not only of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo of Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; of hell. And indéed what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> powers &amp; forces of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings &amp; potentates of the earth do if they be coupled together, and what are they able to do againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt mighty? Surely they are nothing but a vapour of ſmoake that vaniſheth away, and as waxe that melteth at the fire,<note place="margin">Pſ. 58.</note> as ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet. How is it then, wil ſome ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lord deferreth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deliuerance of
<pb facs="tcp:21489:69" rendition="simple:additions"/> his church ſo long? Becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time is not yet come: w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out all doubt he will deliuer it, howſoeuer it be long firſt, and he will breake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head of his aduerſaries in péeces eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as an earthen veſſell,<note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> yea euen by his yron rodde. For ſeeing hée beginneth his iudgement at his own houſe, it is a moſt euident token that hee wil ende it with thoſe that are rebellious againſt his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and that their end ſhal be moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> For they ſhal drinke the dregs of the Lords cuppe when he ſhall viſit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> not in his gentlenes &amp; benignity, as he dealeth with thoſe that are his owne, but in his anger and in his wrath: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this ſhal come to paſſe at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time which hée hath appointed &amp; orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Wherfore it behoueth vs to watch, and in our patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to poſſeſſe our ſoules, and the Lorde ſhall ſhewe vs wonderful things.<note place="margin">Luke 21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But and if you bee terrified through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horrour of the croſſe, of afflictions &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions which are propoſed vnto all thoſe which wil be true diſciples of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon of God, and deſire to be made partakers of his celeſtial kingdome, call to minde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which you haue learned out of the worde
<pb facs="tcp:21489:70" rendition="simple:additions"/> of God: to wit, that the afflictions of the faithful are bleſſed with God, foraſmuch as he hath ſanctified them in the perſon of his ſonne: alſo that they are honorable, foraſmuch as by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the ſufferings of Ieſus Chriſt, and are made like to his image,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 4. Rom. 8.</note> bearing &amp; wearing his liuerie as knightes of his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: alſo that they are tokens &amp; teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the fauour &amp; fatherly will of God, who chaſteneth thoſe whom he loueth, &amp; ſcourgeth euerie childe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he receiueth to himſelf:<note place="margin">Pro. 3. Heb. 12. Apoc. 3.</note> alſo that they be but light and of ſmall continuance being compared w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that weight of moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t glory, which they worke in vs: For if we ſuffer with Ieſus Chriſt we ſhal raigne and be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with him,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle. And bleſſed are they which ſuffer perſecution for righteouſnes ſake for theirs is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of God ſaith Chriſt Ieſus.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1. Mat. 5.</note> Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> afflictions are not onlie profitable for the faithfull, but alſo neceſſarie, foraſmuche as by them the Lorde correcteth that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall corruption &amp; peruerſeneſſe which doth inceſſantly driue vs to rebel againſt his holy comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dements: they tame our fleſh, and bridle it, for feare leaſt it waxe
<pb facs="tcp:21489:70" rendition="simple:additions"/> wanton &amp; goe aſtray: it teacheth vs how to know our ſelues, to forſake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, to waxe out of loue with it, that we may ſo much the more deſire to attain to eternal life: by this meanes we are prouoked to pray &amp; earneſtly to cal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, &amp; to put our truſt in him: our faith &amp; our patience are exerciſed, proued &amp; fined: to be briefe, afflictions are a meane whereby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde procureth and furthereth our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo manie waies, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe which flie from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; which abhorre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhewe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues not only vnaduiſed, but alſo altogether blind &amp; ſworne enemies to their own good and ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Furthermore,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> like as afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (as alſo all thinges els whether proſperity or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity fal out to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good &amp; ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe which loue &amp; feare the Lorde: ſo likewiſe on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary we may ſay that al things turne to a curſe to thoſe which are out of Gods fauour. Wherefore this reſt, this eaſe, theſe good thinges, theſe honors, and theſe temporall commodities which the world promiſeth you, to hinder you from turning to God, ought not to preuaile w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you: And ſurely if you ſuffer your ſelues to be made drunke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſuch deceiuable
<pb facs="tcp:21489:71" rendition="simple:additions"/> allurements, it wil goe ill with you: for he which maketh you ſuch faire promiſes hath no power to performe them: ſo that you ſhal be fruſtrate of your vaine hope, &amp; ſhall become twiſe miſerable. But put caſe you ſhould enioy al theſe things pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceably, you ſhould yet be more accurſed: for they ſhalbe giuen you in the wrath of God, &amp; the vſe thereof ſhal be accurſed to you ſo long as you continue ſeparate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus Chriſt and his Church. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, what profit ſhuld you reap by this to haue the full and whole fruition of all beautifull, precious, &amp; excellent thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are in the worlde, if you looſe your owne ſoules? and what wil you giue in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence thereof ſaith Ieſus Chriſt?<note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> What is there in this world which we ought to count ſo deare &amp; ſo precious as the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſaluation of our ſoules? The ſonne of God made ſo great account of it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe the ſame for vs, he ſhedde his moſt precious bloode, &amp; ſuffered a moſt cruell &amp; a moſt horrible death: not only in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but alſo in his ſoule, foraſmuch as he was put euen as in the preſſe of Gods wrath, and ſuffered the heauie burden of his iuſt iudgement for vs, ſo that he was
<pb facs="tcp:21489:71" rendition="simple:additions"/> in a manner oppreſſed with it, ſo that hée ſaide, <hi>My God, my God why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> We muſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> néeds ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſaluation is a thing of great price, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it coſt the ſonne of God ſo deare. Will you then ſhew your ſelues ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful towardes him as to contemne &amp; treade vnder foote ſo precious &amp; ſo ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable a treaſure? Wil you be ſo cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el and ſo vncurteous to your ſelues as to depriue your ſelues therof for euer, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy tranſitorie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, and to eſcape certaine light and ſmal diſcommodities which are not woorth the naming?</p>
            <p>What man is he ſo mad that wil ſtick to forgoe thrée or foure pence, to gaine a treaſure of one thouſande crownes? Or who is he that is ſo daintie as that hee cannot ſuffer a little pricke of a pinnes point, the paine wherof is gone in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a hand, that he maie be bleſſed &amp; enioye perpetuall pleaſures during his whole life? In like ſort what man is hée that is ſo fooliſh as to hazarde the loſſe of all his goodes vpon hope to get one poore peny: or rather a thing of nothing what man is he that is ſo madde and voyde of reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who to enioy a quarter of an hours
<pb facs="tcp:21489:72" rendition="simple:additions"/> pleaſure would binde him ſelfe to goe vp at the end thereof vpon a ſcaffolde, and there to haue his head cut off, or els to be tormented vpon a whéele. And what are al torments, yea euen the moſt cruel tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes that a man can endure in this world, being compared with the eternall torments, as hath bin ſaid.</p>
            <p>For the honor of God therfore, my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, bethink your ſelues. Come out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curſed Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, return to your fathers houſe, who is ready to receiue you as his children, &amp; to kil the fat calf to the end to feaſt you &amp; to make you good chéere, yea, to apparel you w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the precious orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of his ſon Ieſus Chriſt, after that he hath forgiuen you al your offences. Take héed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you driue not off from day to day, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, for feare leaſt his wrath waxe hoater &amp; hoater againſt you, &amp; leaſt he ſhut the gate of his grace againſt you, when, after you haue ſtopped your eares againſt his aduertiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts you ſhal come to ſéek him in vain. folow him now ſeing he calleth you to him: harde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not your hart againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwéet voice of this moſt merciful father. You haue diſhonored him by your falling away, honor him now, and giue
<pb facs="tcp:21489:72" rendition="simple:additions"/> him glory through your conuerſion: you haue cowardly forſaken the banner of Ieſus Chriſt, gather freſh ſtrength and courage now, ſo that it may appeare that you gaue backe to thend you might leap better, and that you might fight more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly then euer heretofore: you haue denyed and renounced him before men, and haue abiured the truth of the goſpel: make now a quite contrarie abiuration and denyall: renounce Antichriſt in the face of the whole world: abiure all his impieties and abhominations: caſt vp al his filth and infections out of your ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach: you haue offended, diſhonoured, and grieued the poore Church of Ieſus Chriſt: edifie it now and repaire the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thereof: you haue made ſad the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt and all good men, and haue made glad Sathan and Antichriſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their miniſters, do now the quite contrarie: make glad all thoſe to whom you haue miniſtred matter of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and let all thoſe be confounded and aſhamed which reioyce at your fall, and which triumph ouer it: you are gone aſtray, and are againe entred into the way of deſtruction, whence the Lord had
<pb facs="tcp:21489:73" rendition="simple:additions"/> drawne you, returne now againe to the right way which you haue forſaken,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.</note> for feare leaſt that wicked ſpirit which was gone out of your heart, returne againe, that he may enter in againe with ſeauen other ſpirites worſe then himſelfe, leaſt after they haue gotten poſſeſſion of you they make your laſt eſtate worſe then your firſt: that is moſt curſed and moſt miſerable. Now the father of all mercie vouchſafe in mercie to behold you: the high ſhepheard and biſhop of your ſoules vouchſafe himſelfe to looke out his wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering ſhéepe, and to bring it againe to his flocke. The ſpirit of ſtrength and of wiſedome vouchſafe to ſtrengthen and prudently to direct you in all your acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: that all this may redounde to his honour and glorie, to your good and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and to the edification of his church, for the loue of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21489:73"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
